<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The schoole of honest and vertuous lyfe profitable and necessary for all estates and degrees, to be trayned in: but (cheefely) for the pettie schollers, the yonger sorte, of both kindes; bee they men or women. by T.P. Also, a laudable and learned discourse, of the worthynesse of honorable wedlocke, written in the behalfe of all (aswell) maydes as wydowes, (generally) for their singuler instruction, to choose them vertuous and honest husbandes: but (most specialy) sent writte[n] as a iewell vnto a worthy gentlewoman, in the time of her widowhood, to direct &amp; guide her in the new election of her seconde husband. By her approoued freend and kinseman. I.R.</title>
            <author>Pritchard, Thomas, fl. 1579.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850486</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 349:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The schoole of honest and vertuous lyfe profitable and necessary for all estates and degrees, to be trayned in: but (cheefely) for the pettie schollers, the yonger sorte, of both kindes; bee they men or women. by T.P. Also, a laudable and learned discourse, of the worthynesse of honorable wedlocke, written in the behalfe of all (aswell) maydes as wydowes, (generally) for their singuler instruction, to choose them vertuous and honest husbandes: but (most specialy) sent writte[n] as a iewell vnto a worthy gentlewoman, in the time of her widowhood, to direct &amp; guide her in the new election of her seconde husband. By her approoued freend and kinseman. I.R.</title>
                  <author>Pritchard, Thomas, fl. 1579.</author>
                  <author>Wied, Hermann von. Brefe and a playne declaratyon of the dewty of maried folkes.</author>
                  <author>Kingsmill, Andrew, 1538-1569. Viewe of mans estate. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [William How for] Richard Iohnes, and are to be solde at his shop ouer against S. Sepulchers Church without Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1579]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Tho. Pritchard.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>The discourse of wedlock is erroneously attributed to John Rogers. It is actually a revised excerpt of "A viewe of mans estate" by Andrew Kingsmill (STC 15003). "The glasse of godly loue", a reprint of Hermann von Wied's "A brefe and a playne declaratyon of the dewty of maried folkes" (STC 13208), has separate divisional title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15694:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15694:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE SCHOOLE of honeſt and vertuous lyfe: Profitable and neceſſary for all eſtates and degrees, to be trayned in: but (cheefely) for the pettie Schollers, the yonger ſorte, of both kindes; bee they men or Women. by T. P.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, a laudable and learned Diſcourſe, of the worthyneſſe of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Wedlocke, written in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of all (aſwell) Maydes as Wydowes, (generally) for their ſinguler inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to chooſe them vertuous and honeſt Huſbandes: But (moſt ſpecially) ſent writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a Iewell vnto a worthy Gentlewoman, in the time of her widowhood, to direct &amp; guide her in the new election of her ſeconde Huſband. By her approoued freend and kinſeman. I. R.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Johnes, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop ouer againſt S. Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers Church without Newgate.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Reign of Q. Elizabeth Vide P. 41.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15694:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15694:2"/>
                  <head>To the worſhipfull Maiſter <hi>Richard Euerard:</hi> Thomas Pritchard <hi>wiſheth</hi> continuance of health, wealth, and proſperitie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F benefites bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye</hi> beeſtowed, may whet dulled ſenſes, or taſte of receaued curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, ſpurre the cowarde Knight to hazard him ſelfe: I haue good cauſe &amp; occaſion to venture the reproch of people, rather than to ſuffer ſo lyberall a <hi>Micenas</hi> to loſe deſerued fame, or my ſelfe to bee ſpotted with ingratitude, the Mother of vices: which the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſo ſpited and enuied at, that they atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched therwith, were as fellones fully exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted to death. Suppoſinge therfore, it to bee least approchfull, to ſet foorth to the gaze of people my ignorance, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate with the world my ſilly ſentences: than that, my ingratefull acceptions of your liberalitie, ſhould either impaire ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15694:3"/>laudable a qualitie, grafted in your mind, or ſtop the ſame to my Succeſsors. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though that your Worſhips children bee ſo vertuouſly trayned vp, that they neede not the instructions of ſo baſe a Booke: yet J hope it may reclayme the rude rablement of people, to lead a better &amp; more lawdable lot of life. Whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliacion to Vertue, can not bee, with out your condigne praiſe, that diſdayned not to patroniſe my trauell, tendring the ſame. Which though groſely fumbled vp, yet your curteſie is ſuch: that you wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of my meaninge, and weye good will more than this papers Pamphlet, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the ſame. <hi>Alexander</hi> Kinge of <hi>Macedonia</hi> did not weye the cup of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Synaetes</hi> imparted vpon him, but his good wil, ſo J truſt my pretence wil bee accepted more than the thing J greete you with all. And therupon I commit you to Gods good gouernment.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours to commaund. <hi>Tho. Pritchard.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15694:3"/>
                  <head>What is an honeſt lyfe: of what it <hi>conſiſtes, and what it profiteth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that Chriſte created</hi> all thinges, for the behoofe of man: as Braſtes, and Birdes: fiſhe and fleſhe, in the precinctes of the wicked worlde: Laſtly, our Sauiour made man, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all: and as a Stewarde, to vſe theſe his creatures, to ſatiſfie nature, not luſt: to ſet forth his glorye, and not to feede his gluttony: to publiſhe and blaze abroade Chriſt, his potencie, and not like epicures impiouſly to abuſe the ſame. The better to buſie him in his ſtewardſhip, to the intente hée might giue iuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt therof, to his Creator: hée hath, neede of the habite of honeſtie, to exile traiterous inuentions, and to bathe him ſelfe in the Fonte of Vertue, to abandon conſpiring affections. And hauing flighted the tumult of vices, hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liburly of ſinne, and qualitied the flames of the fleſhe, to addicte him ſelfe to lawfull and honeſt lot of lyfe. Which integritie of liuing, is nothing els but in a trade of loyall lyfe, to paſſe brutiſh creatures, and to apply our ſelues to that, which is to God gladſome, and aſſociate to Vertue. <hi>Vertue,</hi> is to flée vice, and to kéepe your ſelues in the bandes and bulwarkes of honeſty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sainct Auſtine</hi> teacheth vertue, to bée the preſcribed meane to liue well and godly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mantuan</hi> the Poet, largely deciphereth, what vertue is, vttereth theſe wordes in her owne perſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I vigent vertue, do dash the doome of fierce fortune, the ſcourge of vices, the banisher of iniquitie, doo dight and trim the mortall, with the fine and fresh hue, of perpetuitie: I lyſt and exalte man, made of duſt and ashes, to participate ioyes immortall. The Sunne can do nothing with his bright beames, and ſplendant goulden Banner: the Moone with her light, and chriſtall cleareneſſe: the Starres with their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15694:4"/>twinckling glances, without my preſence: If I perishe, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe mounteth, gluttonie gloryeth, vice vaunteth, pryde is pampred, fayth infeebled, religion contempned, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, for demure manners, miraculous murders: for pietie, prauitie: and for heauenly contemplation, inuaſion of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in his Booke of bringing vp youthe, ſhoweth the effectes thereof, defininge her, vnder the habite and title of Philoſophie: ſayinge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vertue doth declare what is good and godly, foule and fulſome: how wée ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues towardes our Parentes, our elders, ſtraungers, Officers, &amp; Magiſtrates, fréends, ſeruaunts, and all others. As to giue God duetifull reuerence, to Parentes humble obeyſance, to Magiſtrates lawful obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to bee modeſt to inferiors, not puffed with pryde in proſperitie, nor deſperate in pouertie, not prone to pleaſure, méeke and gentle, ſtill obſeruinge the merry meane, adiudged vertue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lucillius</hi> that paſſing Poet, ſayth that it is a vertue, to know the good from the bad: to decline from vicious and vnſatiable affections, and to labour to attayne honour, through newneſſe of life, and amendment of manners.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The deuiſion of Vertue.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>CIcero,</hi> that gay Gardener, and cunning Arborer, hath grafted vpon this Trée of Vertue: foure braue bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: out of which, bud many ſpringing ſproutes, very neceſſary and ſpectant to perfection, and heale the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maymes of mans life. That is, <hi>Prudence, Iuſtice, Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Fortitude:</hi> which foure, as in appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions diuerſe, ſo in proofe and practice diſſonant. Yet the true genitors of honeſt lyfe, and meane methode, of lyuing, which <hi>Macrob.</hi> witneſſeth: in his Booke <hi>De ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Scipionis,</hi> particularly imparting, to each of them: a ſeueral goodly guiſt of action.</p>
                        <p>To <hi>Prudence,</hi> polliticke conueiance, and duetifull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15694:4"/>to wil, that is good and godly, ſincere and ſauery: and to diſſanull nought and noyſome, and with diuine prouidence, to be prompte and ready, to ſhunne iminent daungers.</p>
                        <p>To doughty Dame <hi>Fortitude,</hi> it is as duety addicted, not to feare fainting fittes, not to be diſmayde, but with cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous aſſertions, or fulſome factes, not to bee lulled in the Cradell of Securitie, in pleaſaunt proſperitie: nor yoked with miſery, to pant in pouertie. This <hi>Fortitude</hi> is not mans might, or ſtubberne ſtrength of the armes onely, but it muſt growe to the habite of vigent Vertue, and bee garded and gouerned, with preceptes of reaſon, inuironed with the inſtitutions of milde manners, and merry meane, which ſhall yéelde the poſſeſſor magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in countenaunce, conſtancy in aſſertions, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenauntes, bountiful magnificencie, and vaunted valy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antneſſe.</p>
                        <p>To Lady <hi>Temperance,</hi> is adioyned this ſway in mans life, that the poſſeſſor may not couet thinges worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, nor perpetrat the deſert of <hi>Peccaui:</hi> inthraling his affections to the yoake of reaſon. This loyall Lady, hath to her aſſociate and handmaydes, <hi>Modeſtie, Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, Abſtinence, Chaſtitie, Honeſtie, Moderation,</hi> and <hi>Sobrietie.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To the péereles pearle <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> is highted for gallaunt guift, to contribute to euery man his owne: from which bewtified braunch of Vertue, theſe iolly Gemmes, haue originall: <hi>Innocencie, Amitie, Concorde, Pietie, Religion, Affection,</hi> and <hi>Humanitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero,</hi> the Father of fluent and filed Phraſe of ſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, attributeth to this vertue, many pretty profitable properties. Firſt, not to iniury any man, without great adhibited cauſe and occaſion. Secondarily, to vſe things common, commonly: not diducting them to priuate profit or pleaſure. This accordinge to <hi>Tullie,</hi> is grounded on Grauitie, founded on Fidelitie, and ſeaſoned with Sobrietie.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15694:5"/>
                           <hi>Lactantius,</hi> in his ſixt Booke, alotteth to Iuſtice, double function: firſt, to annexe, and to vnite vs to God, through Religion. Secondly with man, through pure paſſions of pittie and humanitie.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The rewarde of Vertue or honeſt lyfe.</head>
                        <p>IF any dowltiſh dullarde, bée ſo blinde and bleared of ſight, ſo incarcered, in the Denne of darkeneſſe: that hee can not ſee the bright beames, and royall rewarde of vertuous and honeſt life: I wiſh him to know the prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence of Vertue, and the honourable harbor of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, to bathe there tenante in the bliſſe of felicitie, to aduaunce him by the goulden gay guifte of promotion, in this worlde: And as the péereleſſe Poet <hi>Virgill</hi> ſayth, in the world to come, to aſcende the ſtarry ſkie, to haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall fruition of ioyes euerlaſting.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lactantius</hi> to the vertuous, aſcribeth this renowmed rewarde, to bée able for to infring and repell, the outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious onſet of wofull wrath, to moderate and bow backe with the bit of honeſty, the ſore aſſaults of lecherous luſt, to daſh the diueliſh dint of dreadfull deſires.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Plautus</hi> writeth that vertue excelleth all thinges: lyfe, libertie, health, wealth, depende and haue their beeinge therof.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Claudianus</hi> extollinge vertue: affirmeth, that ſhée hath no néede of Torches or lightſome Linkes, to bewray her ſplendant hue in the night, nor ſtore of gliſtering gould in the day, to clime the ſtears of preferment: but houering on the ſtately ſtages of dignitie and honour: inuiteth her folowers, to taſte the bliſfull fruite of their toyle and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. Will not this hale the Howlets that delight in darkeneſſe, to the embraſing of vertue, and inſpired with her verdure, by litle and litle attaine the perfection ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Labour for light: damne your darke delightes, and toyle for this treaſure.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15694:5"/>
                     <head>The hinderance of vertue, and how it is attayned. Chap. 2.</head>
                     <p>THe famous and learned, trowpe of Philoſophers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of fclicitie, compoſed of multitude of vertues, as of ſingular ſimples, haue interdicted the ſtudentes of Dame <hi>Vertue,</hi> of the contaminatinge contraries, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames therof. Among whom, <hi>Cicero,</hi> a princely piller of Philoſophie: commendinge Abſtinence, the freendly forderer of vertuous actions, bountifully abandoneth, and carefully condempneth poyſoninge pleaſures, as baytes of vice, and heaper of harmes, and ſayth: the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous man can not atchiue to the tipe of Vertue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Valerius Max.</hi> ſworne to Abſtinence, auoucheth that the Cittie cituated on pleaſure, drowned with delight, can not long laſt nor maintaine her liberties, and fréedomes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lactantius</hi> Chronicled in his fourth Booke, thrée waies to come by Vertue: the firſt, to abſtaine from lewde la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and wicked workes: The ſecond, from wilful wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wordes, corrupting good manners: The third, from the muſe and meditacion of miſchéefe. Hee that aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the firſt ſteppe of theſe ſteares, is adiudged iuſt: the ſeconde, vertuous: the thirde, ſheweth his aſcendent to haue the perfect patron of God, his Creator.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Horace</hi> commending Abſtinence, ſayth, Vertue to bee nothing but abſtaining from vice: therfore, leauing it a Guide to the Goddes vertue, my Penne poſteth to Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as an inſtrument neate and neceſſary, to accoſt this habite of Vertue, and honeſt tried trade of life. As the ruddy Roſe odoriferous in ſwéete ſmell, is growinge in brierie buſhes, harming the hand that catcheth thereat: So is Dame <hi>Vertue</hi> placed in difficulte Dales, and can not bee obtained without great labours, ſweates and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe trauels. Which (as <hi>Heſiodus</hi> witneſſeth) as the pearcing prickes of Briers, perſwade the luſtned eyes to leaue the Roſe, for feare of hurt happeninge therby: ſo continuall contemplation of goodnes, ſtill in conflict with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15694:6"/>vice, laborious abſtinence, and the wiriſomneſſe of mind, will inſinuat the ſtudent, to paſſe and poſte to pleaſures: yea, that few or none without curidus caueats of enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng enfiſements, can perſiſt and perfeuer, to arine in the puiſſant princely Porte of Vertue, and heauenly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Honeſtie. In ſaylyng to this Harbour, the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers ſpent more Water, than Wine, addicted to due diet, not to delicious delightes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laertius,</hi> in his booke of the liues of Philoſophers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, euerie diſcipline and royall regiment of lawfull life, to want thrée thinges, nature, documents, good prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: that is to wit, ſcience, and exerciſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt to diſcourſe of witte, and wiſe diſpoſition, <hi>Plato</hi> proueth, that pregnant wit, is an inſtrument of Vertue, and that there is no parfect prudent parſon, but that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedyngly excelleth all others. And if you peruſe the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable liues of famous Philoſophers, euen there ſhall yée finde, princely prayſe highted their perſonages, and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly glorified for pregnancie of wit. Of which <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> appoynteth two fréendly functions: the one, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray falſehood, and couert conueance: the other, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fidelitie and truthe. And by witte, wée muſt differre from brutiſh beaſtlineſſe, whoſe heads heaped with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, reſpect only preſent pleaſures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tully,</hi> toyling to know and finde out the moſt apparant proofes of Vertue in man, faith, in his <hi>Tuſculanes queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> it to bee wit: And if the Selles and Sellers of the remples of the Head, be ſeaſoned with the Odoriferous verdure therof: the pure and perfit patterne of vertue muſt ſprynge therefro.</p>
                     <p>The Philoſophers would not almoſt admit to the Lore of learnyng any, but ſutche as by proofe paſſed, and by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all had the trimme treaſure of wit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quintilian,</hi> ſaith: That if a man lacke this harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Vertue, preceptes and rules of diſcipline, auayle as mutche, as Tillage, to bare and barren ſoyle: whoſe frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te and increaſe, may not counteruayle the toyle and tranell therein.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15694:6"/>Eraſmus, whom tracte of time made more ſuttle ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of ingenious impes, ſaith: That the dull witted boye, may by diligence, whet it, to attempte excellente exploytes of Diſcipline: For it is apparant, that Nature may be repelled (though <hi>Horace</hi> holde the contrarie.)</p>
                     <p>For <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> blab and bleat of ſpéeche, by puttynge of certayne ſtones into his mouthe, to cure and fill vp the imperfection and mayme of Nature, attayned to the vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance and ſugred ſpéeche of honored Orators, through adhibited déede and diligence. To mitigate and alaye, the rayge of this colde comfort, touchyng the ſléepie pated perſons: wee reade that <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> had two ſchollers, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi> and <hi>Theopompius,</hi> the one, ingenious and egre to attayne knowledge: the other, néedyng the ſpurre, to aſpier the attempted ſcope. To conclude, this tracte of witte, and prayſed promptneſſe of conceiuynge: by ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſentence, and by opinion of Philoſophers, I gather, the ſooneſt ripe, to be ſooner rotten: and the hard headded felow, hauing attained the habitte of perfection, and edge of excellencie, to paſſe him whome firſte, I braued with bragges. <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> highly had in honour, for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and iollie iudgement in faculties, by reaſon of brode blowen blaze of commendation: had a boye of ripe witte, preſented by his fréendes, to declayme beefore him. The fréendely furtherers of the buyſied boye, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectynge his iudgement, were anſwered by him: Timely ripe, timely rotten.</p>
                     <p>But, the ouerthrow of ripe conceauinge, commeth by ſecuritie, and ouer great confidence therein: for truſting to the maturitie of wit, they ſo longe linger in layſineſſe, that either they amit and quenche the qualitie thereof, or with ſtrayning it with extraordinarie meanes, mayme and marre the ſame.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>¶ Of inſtruction.</head>
                        <p>AS an Horſe or Coult, be he neuer ſo tame and apte of nature, cannot ſerue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſe of man without breaking:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15694:7"/>So a man, bée hee neuer ſo ingenious and inritched, by wit and ripe conceauing, without preceptes and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can not ſcale, nor aſcend the high and haughtie Hil of <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> to bée acquainted with the Ladies of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, nor climbe the craggie Cliffes and clymates of knowledge: which poſition, <hi>Cicero</hi> ſincerely fortifieth ſaying: That inſtruction doth corroborate and fortifie the gyfte of wit and nature, and for that cauſe, <hi>Gentilis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded firſt, Schooles to bée errected in <hi>Athence,</hi> a Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Greece,</hi> that the couente of youth, might bee there inſtructed.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> a learned Philoſopher, compared the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a ſtone: and béeing demaunded by a fooliſh Father, what learninge auayled his Sonne: hee anſwered, that a ſtone had no place in their Theators, or place of prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, meaning the vnlearned.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Ethnickes,</hi> ſtudious of erudicion and knowledge, kept an inſtructor in their houſes, to trayne vp their youthes in the pleaſant pathe of Nurtur and knowledge: which thing, ſo well lyked the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that it was, as Law enacted, that the children, which were not traded vp in erudicion, ought not to fauour their Fathers, or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der curteſies to them, inféebled with age.</p>
                        <p>To attaine the treaſure of Vertue, and gaine the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fome guift of Diſcipline, there bee two kindes of inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: one mute, the other ſowndable: mute, as when wee ſtudy our ſelues, diſcourſinge without wordes, the carued carracters, and woorkes of others: The other, when the inſtructor or teacher, with ſounding voyce, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the miſteries and hidden hardnes, of others labors. This laſt manner of inſtructing, the learned lore, aboue others commend: <hi>Pythagoras, Empedocles, Democritus,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> his Peregrinations, ſayling ouer Surge and Sirtes of Seas, to heare Lectures, verifie the ſame: who were not content to like of their priuate ſtudies. Leaſt I ſhould ſpend my winde in waſte, in diſcourſinge of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and paſſe the Campe, in which, youthes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15694:7"/>ought to bee trained vp: I decipher them as folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
                        <p>Pithie Poemes, heroyicall holſome Hiſtories, Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Philoſophie, ſacred and ſincere Scripture, the ſalue of ſinfull ſores, and pathe to Paradice.</p>
                        <p>The gracious <hi>Grecians,</hi> thought (only) Poets to be wiſe, and therfore in honeſt Poetrie did firſt ſeaſon the tender ingenie of Impes, the better to aſpire to furder felicitie of Science.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Horace,</hi> ſingularly ſéene in the art, in his Epiſtles, exhorteth Children to be firſt inſtructed in Poetrie, as an Inſtrument neceſſary, to pollice and file away the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of liſping nature, and that it ſoweth and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in their heedy heades, the ſeede of Sapience, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and knowledge.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Diodorus</hi> ſayde, it was a fine and famous thinge, for man by others crymes and faultes, to cure him of that care, and medicine and heale his infirmities, which the reading of Hiſtories, Monumentes, déedes of other men ſhall guide vs to doo.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Baeroaldus</hi> ſayth, that Hiſtories inflameth a man to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, enamoreth him with vertue, reprooueth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and exileth vice.</p>
                        <p>To ſtand vpon choyce of Philoſophie, the very <hi>Ecimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> of the worlde, which wée interpret and conſter, a Louer of knowledge, or imbracer of wiſedome, foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all Bookes of that noble Science, to bee ſpectant to ſurueye the lyfe of man: As the <hi>Ethickes</hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> impugning the rebellion of vice, brydling the frenſie fits of flaming fleſh, with the bit of Nurture and manners, The <hi>Pollitickes</hi> inſtructe vs, called to the function of a Magiſtrate, to miniſter Iuſtice, to the exilement of vice, and inhaunſing of Vertue.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lactantius</hi> writ a worthy worke of Diuine inſtitutions. <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> of the inſtitutinge of a chriſtian Prince? with infinit others, commodious for the regiment of the lyfe of man.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15694:8"/>Laſtlye, fitly furniſhed, and decently decked with inſtitutions of the ſurueyed Sciences: wee muſt imploy our ſelues, to viewe the valleys of ſacred Scriptures, which teache vs to know our Sauiour, and him onely to worſhippe: which as <hi>Lactantius</hi> writeth, is the true Philoſophie.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Pouertie impareth not Vertue.</head>
                        <p>EXperience hauing taught mée, a ſilly ſort of fooliſh fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes to withdraw them ſelues from ſtudie, to heede handy craftes, I thought by excellent examples, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted reaſons, to heale that paſſion of infirmitie, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their faynting fittes, the better to abide the yoake of knowledge.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Apuleus</hi> ſayth in his time, none became famous, but ſuch as were annoyed with nakedneſſe, and cloyde with carefull dyet, from the houre of birthe: And hee boldely blazeth this commendacion of Pouertie, that in thoſe dayes, it was the builder of Citties, the maintainer of Equitie and Science.</p>
                        <p>Wée reade a worthy example of <hi>Cleanthes</hi> a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, who pinched with pouertie in youth: in the night ſeaſon haled vp water in Buckets, which hée ſould in the day to maintaine his ſtudie. If our Engliſh Fathers were ſo inflamed with the loue of Learninge: no doubte our Realme royally ruled, would bée a precious patron to all <hi>Europe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſayth, Vertue to haue a ſting, meaning labour, which plucked awaye by ſufficiencie of knowledge, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth the bier in bliſſe.</p>
                        <p>Here may riſe a queſtion, whither the vnlearned may attaine Vertue or no, the which queſtion is reſolued by <hi>Tullie</hi> in his Orations, who ſaith that hee had ſocietie with a multitude of men, both godly, honeſt, and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yea, altogeather voyde of knowledge: I annexed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15694:8"/>this Sentence to my matter, leaſt deſperation ſhould bee infixed, &amp; gréeuouſly ingrafted in the harts of vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned dottrels.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Of vſe and exerciſe.</head>
                        <p>IF a man bee armed with the fine furniture of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Dame <hi>Nature,</hi> beautified with the gaye Gownes of Witte, and Diſpoſition: yet if Diligence bee diſmiſte, and Practice put aſide, all is vaine, for the beeinge and continuance of Vertue, is in action and exerciſe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero,</hi> whoſe doughty diligence, aduaunced to dignitie and high calling among the <hi>Romaines:</hi> inſtructeth vs in his Rhetorickes, that preceptes and rules of diſciplines anayle nothinge, without daily diligence and paynefull practice therof.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lactantius,</hi> in his thirde Booke, writeth that Artes bee learned and layde for, that gotten, agréeable practice and conuerſation may ariſe therof.</p>
                        <p>For <hi>Tullie</hi> ſayth, it is a ſmall praiſe to know Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and not to doo therafter. Man mindefull of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſtudious thereof, muſt imitate the buſie Bées, who in flagrante Sommer, flee abroade ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge of diuerſe Flowers, and of each pickinge reléefe, ſtore vppe, and heape much Honny: So ought a man exerciſe him ſeife daily, vntill he hath gotten the trimme treaſure of Vertue and Learninge, and the better to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to your purpoſe: in youthfull yeares, vſe foure wayes.</p>
                        <p>The firſt, in readinge, ſelecte and picke out of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Authors, fine filed Phraſes, and leaſt the treaſurs houſe of Man, I meane his memory, bee robbed therof, haue them Chronicled in the ſkirtes of a Booke. And ſo of euery Science.</p>
                        <p>Which thinge <hi>Plynie</hi> practiced, of whom writeth his Vnckle, the ſecond of that name.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15694:9"/>The ſecond is, to follow <hi>Macrobius</hi> Preceptes, teaching vs to vſe and exerciſe the good, and to baniſh the euill: for what ſo euer are written. they bee for our learninge: for as the meate lodged in the mouth, or clungde in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, feedeth not the body, nor hath not concoction, for lacke of naturall heate, to diſgeſt the ſame into good blood and mayntenance of the body. So doth not reading profit, except it be conuerted to the behoofe of the weale publick, neither is the ſtudents conſcience diſcharged: For <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith in his Offices, that wee bee borne partly to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and profit our fréendes, our Parentes, and moſt of all, our natiue Countrey.</p>
                        <p>The thirde, is to do ſome thing (worth the while) euery day, as <hi>Appelles</hi> the conning Paynter, who though cloyed and ouercharged with a heape of hindraunces, yet daylie drue a line, and paynted ſome precious protrature, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fame.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Heſiodus</hi> ſayth: Many littels makes a mickell. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt wee greedily gapinge, gulpe vp knowledge to bury it in our bellyes, as churles doo their ſubſtance and money: but imploy it ſo, that the Innocente may reape thereby vtilitie and ſaluation: and wee muſt make flow ſpeed, accordinge to <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars Adaige,</hi> leaſt before wee be fully grounded, wee babble to draw others to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, a cauſe of ſundry ſectes in England this daye, more is the pittie.</p>
                        <p>It is far better, by dilligence to reade a litle well, and with addiſement, than running (as they ſay) at randon, voyde of reaſon, to talke of the Moone ſhine in the water, ſuppoſinge though their heads bee filled with humors of vaine glory, that they perceiue not their doultiſh delights and vanitie of ſpeeche: that others of ſound iudgemente, will not condempne them as vayne glorious bablers.</p>
                        <p>I can compare ſuche fellowes to a bragginge Paynter, who in the preſence of <hi>Appelles,</hi> cheefe of the Science, brau'd it out with bragges, that ſodainly &amp; in the twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of an eye, hee had made a fine well proportioned
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15694:9"/>Image: <hi>Appelles</hi> knowing his ſinglenes of ſkill, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Such paultry protratures, thou cauſt make ynough: than viewing it, ſayd: it was doone quicke ynough, if wel ynough.</p>
                        <p>That ſage ſaying of <hi>Cato</hi> the wiſe, may abate and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the hot courage of ouer haſty Miniſters now a daies: which preſſe to preache, before they haue the ground of their worke, or know the foundation of true religion, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troniſed by our royal and gracious Quéene? How ſprang vp ſedicious ſectes in the Church, but through haſtie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent bablers, preſuminge to goe to Pulpit when the Carte cryed for them.</p>
                        <p>The fourth kinde of exerciſe, <hi>Philelphus</hi> ſayd, <hi>Cato</hi> the wiſe ſage <hi>Senat</hi> to haue vſde: which was at night to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat and ſuruey his trauell that daye, and to require ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of his owne reading: and it was decréede amonge the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> that the Table couered and meate brought and layde theron, that the Maiſters and cheeſe of euery Cittie, ſhould call the youthes in, and demaund and exigate, what they had profited that day: and hee that had doone nothing, was barde their company, as vnworthy to eate.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Apuleius</hi> wiſheth men, and ſpecially Churche men, and Schollers, with the ſtudentes of Vertue: to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the nature of the Shéepe, which at night incarcered with hurdels, and cloſets, chue the kud: yea all the graſſe eaten and geathered that day: which chuynge, yéeldeth a ſecond fruite or milke to the ſhéepe Maiſter: ſo ſhould euery man doo of his reading: for at night they ſhould cal it to minde, to imploy it to the ſeconde vſe or profit, that is, to the common wealth to edifie the vnlearned people, which ignorantly run headlong to vice.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>What decent behauiour, Vertue, and honeſtie is to bee obſerued in our proper perſons, and in euery age. Chap. 3.</head>
                     <p>MAcrobius ſayth, that Vertue doth conſiſte in two things, that is, in honeſt behauiour and ſhow of him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15694:10"/>ſelfe, and in godly diſpoſition towardes others: for a man muſt of neceſſitie be able to gouerne himſelfe, before hée be admitted and thought worthy to haue ſubmiſſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Firſt, we muſt bridell our owne licentious lewde liuing, and inthrall to the yoke of reaſon, our furious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, erre wée bee highted to the dignitie of the facred ſeate of a magiſtrate. Herevpon, a wiſe man, eſpiynge a wanton witleſſe magiſtrate, ſpurd a queſtion to <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Mileſius</hi> the Philoſopher: Who was a kinde kyng and worthie his ſeate? He anſwered: He that gouerneth wel him ſelf. That euery one may learne to rule him ſelfe, I wiſh theſe preceptes folowynge to bée obſerued, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the plotte of Memorie.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, that a man be addicted to ſcilence, more than to talke: for taciturnitie argueth wiſdome: and bablyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraieth a foole. <hi>Macrobius</hi> ſayd, a Philoſopher to make as greate a ſigne and ſhoe of Learnyng by ſcilence, as by talke. <hi>Apuleius</hi> doth write, that <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> a ſinguler inſtructer of youth, was wonte, firſt to ſeaſon the twat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng tungues of his diſciples, with the vertue ſcilence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Socrates,</hi> demaunded, how man might become wiſe? He adiured the perſon to obſerue two preceptes: the one to huyſht rather than to ſpeake: the other, for to learne how to ſpeake.</p>
                     <p>Dame Nature prouident of the vertue ſcilence, and of the conſequent commodities thereof, incarcered our tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in a Turret, inuironed with ſharpe téethe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, if like witleſſe wiues it ſhould miſcarie to annoy any man, with ſtaynyng hue or blottes of defame. And wée haue two eares and one tongue, to heare more than wée ſhould vnadniſedly blabbe abroade.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Romaines,</hi> embracers of this vertue, had erected in their trim Temples, lofted on Theaters <hi>Angerona</hi> Goddeſſe of Scilence, with her lippes ſeard vp. And the <hi>Egiptians</hi> ſo honored <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> God of taciturnitie, that his princely protrature, was painted in euery houſe with his ſingers lockyng his lippes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15694:10"/>Xenocrates, ſcilent in companie, was aſked the cauſe of his ſadneſſe &amp; ſcilence? Hee ſhapte this anſwer: That there with hee was neuer annoyed, but inconuenience accident by talke, graueld him daily, and duely. If a man bee ſpurred to ſpeake: let him haue ſpéeche of thinges fit for the place, time, and company: Nexte, interrupt none in their talke, nor correct it, leaſt thou be deemed a buſie body. An other precept wée haue inioyned vs, to kepe that which is a meane and meaſurable order in our talke which <hi>Terence</hi> commendeth in his Comedie, called <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> with theſe wordes: I thinke a meane to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious in mans life, and worthy embracinge: therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the learned ſayde, Vertue to be the ſame, the which <hi>Horace</hi> doth confeſſe in his Epiſtles, ſaying: <hi>Eſt modus in rebus &amp;c.</hi> Engliſhed thus:</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>In things ther is a merry meane, and bounds for to be kept, The which to paſſe or to impaire, no vertue may bee reapt.</head>
                        <p>WHen the ſeauen wiſe Philoſophers, imprinted their ſapient and politicke Poſies vpon the walles of the Senat houſe, <hi>Cleobulus Lyndus,</hi> one and chéefe of the number, with his fine fingers writ this ſage Sentence: <hi>The meane is beſt in all thinges,</hi> as an inſtruction worthy aduertiſement and impreſſion in the memory of man.</p>
                        <p>Another Caueat I will adioyne, that in talking wee doo not carpe nor quip ſome ſilly ſoule, as ſubiecte to vice or infirmitie, which other of ſharper intelligence eſpie in vs: for <hi>Diogenes</hi> warned vs to exile our preſence, that vice which wee reproue as foule and fulfome in an other.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, that hee ought to be ſpotleſſe, that with dire defame ſurueyeth others infirmities: If a man view both endes of the Wallet, he ſhalbe ſo ouer charged with the weight of vices packt behinde, that hee will not annoy with nippes, others of honeſter lyuinge: For it behocueth a man to pull the beame out of his owne eye, ere hee can eſpye the mote in his Brothers.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15694:11"/>As annexed to this cryme, I admoniſh the gentle Reader that hee be ſetled in ſtate, not pufte vp with the bliſſull blaſt of fawning Fortune, nor dolefully indure diſtreſſe, imitating <hi>Socrates:</hi> who was neuer mooued, to heare of his heauy happes, nor prowde, prayſed for excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploytes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Plato</hi> was demaunded how a wiſe man was knowen? He anſwered: hée that is not angry, beeinge diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor prowd for adhibited prayſe. And why? becauſe that pride and wrath bee the extreames of Vertue, and the faire mannered man, knoweth them not. If a man perpend and conſider the euent of pleaſure, and ſawning bliſſe of froward Fortune, hee had more neede to follow the deede and dooinge of <hi>Hermolaus,</hi> who in proſperitie mourned, than others that glow and glory therein: For after faire weather, commeth rayne: and there is no ſuch fulneſſe, but after comes as great an ebbe. Fortune is variable, as appeareth by <hi>Camenus</hi> a ritche man, who ſo bathed him ſelfe in bliſſe, and aboundaunce of wealth, that hee neuer taſted of woe, or miſchaunce.</p>
                        <p>Vpon a time for repaſt, he went to ſee ſilly Fiſhermen caſtinge their Nettes, and fingering their traſh to feede his humors, his Signet fell into the Sea: well ſayd hée, now I know that euil Fortune doth raigne: The ſecond day, as they drue their Nettes, they caught a goodly Cod, which for a rare and goodly guift, they imparted vpon the Gentleman: His Cooke gobbetinge the ſame, in his entrayles founde his Maiſters Signet, who with excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge gladneſſe, and chearefull grace, preſented it to his Maiſter: who blinded with the bliſſe of Fortune, ioyfully receaued it, imparting vpon his Seruaunt a iolly Iuell, named, <hi>Nihil,</hi> and perſwaded him ſelfe that Fortune ſo fauoured his Maiſterſhip, that hee could not miſcarry in any exployte, or attempt, To bee fully reſolued of deſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Fortune: hee tooke a corde, I meane a Halter, and in a brauery, aſſayed how it became a ritch man, or how that gallant cheyne, would fit Fortunes heire or dandled
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15694:11"/>dottrell: ſtanding vpon a ſtoole, Fortune burthened and laden with the care of this life, champion like, hee tiſped his féete beſide: Fortune frowning at his folly, ſuffered her long lulled lubber, to ſtranguiſh and hang to death.</p>
                        <p>Thus ought wee to conceaue no pride in felicitis, nor diſpaire in diſtreſſe and pouertie: It was wel and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſayd of <hi>Plautus</hi> in <hi>Amph.</hi> that it ſéemed good to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gods, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after pleaſure, ſhould ſuccéed paine: as after labor, eaſe.</p>
                        <p>This excellent example, may batter the buildinges of Fortune in our daies, and may diſgrace them inhaunſed therby. Wherfore, let euery man labour to liue vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, to the example of others: And as coye Curtezans and daintie Dames, haue their gliſtering Glaſſes to bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and correcte their attier, or cumly countenance, ſo ſhould euery man haue a godly perſon, for a patterne to liue by, whoſe ſteps ſtudied on, ſhuld guide him to vertue.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Of the diuerſitie of ages and yeares, and what manners is proper to them.</head>
                        <p>KNowinge by the aduertiſment of <hi>Terence,</hi> and other learned Authors, that change of yeares, requireth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepancy of manners, and alteration of condicions: I thought it to bee woorth the while, to Chronickle in the ſkirtes of this baſe Booke, the ſeuerall duties of all ages: Findinge in Authors, the yeares of man to bee deuided into ſixe ſeuerall wayes, and manners of lyuing: I will anchore and annexe to them their proper functions.</p>
                        <p>And firſt, to begin with Infancie, or Babeſhip, who for weakeneſſe of nature is not reformable, though ſinfull: therfore we wil commit his gouernance, to the diſcretion of his Mother or Nurce.</p>
                        <p>Next and ſecond, is childehood, hauing the vſe of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whoſe toungs and mindes like a Painters cloth, is fit for to receaue euery hue or colour. Wherfore their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to be ſeaſoned with the verdure of Vertue, euen from their Cradels: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new veſſel wil taſt euer, or long of the firſt lickor: they muſt than be taught to prooue and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15694:12"/>grow a Chriſtian, as they doo in ſtrength and yeares.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Apuleius</hi> ſaydithe childe that prooueth ſtrong in bones, by benefit of bountifull nature, and a Mouſter in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to be better vnborne, then to haue fruition of life to comaculat, with defame &amp; vnperfect behauiour his pley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers &amp; fréends. For one rotten ſhéepe annoyeth a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: In <hi>Greece</hi> it was vſed, that the Father &amp; Maiſter, was puniſhed for the childes offence, if fondly they fauoured crime committed, worthy chaſticemente, and correction.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Diogenes</hi> eſpying a Scholler playing the wanton, with his ſtaffe beate his Maiſter.</p>
                        <p>If pampering Parents, were at this day ſo executed, it would fare better with youthes and teachers. They will not follow the right path of education of children, ſet forth by <hi>Philel.</hi> who in his Booke of Education of children, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth fooliſh Fathers, &amp; mad Mothers, to inſtruct their children to know God their Creator, to bee obediente to them in word and déede, to be humble to their Superiors, gentle to their equals, milde in manners, not teachinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to bable, to lie, to be ſlothful, to go ſlouenly in their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel, vnwaſht or fulſome any way, if vortuouſly they bée traded vp, béeing tender twigs, &amp; impes, they muſt of neceſſitie grow to perſection of manners in tract of time.</p>
                        <p>The thirde age, is called of the Lateniſtes, <hi>Iuuentus,</hi> of <hi>Iuuo,</hi> for the childe paſſinge the time of ſeauen yeares, is able to ayde his Parentes, accordinge to the engliſh of <hi>Iuuo,</hi> to ayd: In which, <hi>Quintilian</hi> writeth, that ſuch as bee vſed in that time and yeares, to curious cates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes, ſweete meates, will euer looke for the ſame: and iudgeth that to be the cauſe of murthers, theftes, and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries: For youthes ſo delicately nuſted, comminge to mans eſtate, wil by hooke or by crooke, come by and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame: for ſuch as be vſed to delicate diet, except good qualities adorne and boulſter it out, their ſugred luſt will condempne their bodies. Wée reade of one <hi>Maxillus</hi> a Noble man, whoſe princely Parents know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge their Sonne to be borne to large liuinges, &amp; print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15694:12"/>poſſeſſions, deliciouſly dandled theſe auſter auſpring to mans ſtate, without any good gouernance, or inſtruction: after the deceaſe of his Parentes, rulinge by rigor, his ſubiectes, hatinge him for extremitie, perpetrated and doone to them, with force banniſht him his Lande: The poore Pilgrim vſed to fine fare, hauing not <hi>vnde,</hi> as the Lateniſtes ſay, fell to robbing, to maintaine daintines of dyet, and taken with the manner, was dampned to die: By this you may ſée, that the aſſertion of learned <hi>Quintilian</hi> was true: that what ſo euer they bee vſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſuch they will ſtill haue.</p>
                        <p>In this age of <hi>Iuuentus,</hi> the youthes of the <hi>Romans,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to hange vp vpon the Pinackles of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, certaine colours, or laces: as Monumentes of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed age, and in tokens of virilitie taken on them, &amp; were cloathed in faire white gownes, to ſignifie to the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled troupe and company, that they would leade a cleaner &amp; ſadder life, conſonant to their attier &amp; externall habite.</p>
                        <p>This care the auncient <hi>Romans</hi> toke, to traine vp their children in Vertue, which may bee for the reformation of Engliſh Fathers, and fréendly fortherers of youth. As in all ages God is to bee honoured, Parentes obeyed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors heeded vnto, ſo I wiſh it in this, that beeing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers them ſelues, they may to Gods glory, &amp; their fame, and eaſe, prudently trade vp their owne.</p>
                        <p>The fourth is <hi>Adoleſcencie,</hi> hauing trod vnder foot .xiiij. yeares, in which wée begin to fantſie &amp; ſéeke after world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſures, as gallaunt Geluings, hounds, to rowſe the lodged Bucke, or hunt the Haare and other exerciſes: in which yeares man may haue great geſſe, &amp; coniecture of nature and diſpoſition: This age continueth till, xviij. in which all vices bee grafted and planted: as to haunt harlots, to proue prodigall, prowd, laſciuious: and to end: than be they careles, ſubiect to ſayle with euery blaſte: in this they haue moſt néede of the ſpurre, to reclaime them from vices: the vigor and feruency of youthfull Adoſeſcencie is ſutche, that it ſo inflameth their buiſie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15694:13"/>bodies, to luſt, after tranſitorie traſh: it ſo blindeth their bleared eyes, that moylyng and wilfully wallowynge in the lotheſome lake of Letcherie, and ſinke of ſinne, they cannot ſee, nor diſcerne the pleaſant pathe of righteous and godly conuerſation. Euen as the fume of Claret wyne, boylyng through exceſſe in the ſtomacke, bleareth the eyes, ſo doth the hurtfull heate of adoleſcencie, that they cannot ſée to diuerte, from the puddle of perdition. Therefore, it is pertinent to the true touche of maiſters, and ſpecially ſpectant to parents, whom care admoniſheth to cure their infirmities: to warne them, if they be flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſéemelineſſe of ſhape, comelineſſe of complexion, proper compaction, and fine framynge of luſtie limmes, that they truſt not thereto. For <hi>Virgill,</hi> eſpyinge the pride of a boy, by meanes of his fayre face, ſaid: My fayre boye, truſt not too mutche to bewtie, for it ſoone fadeth: Bewtie is but a blaſt, there is no floriſhyng flower ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and freſh of hue, but in ſpace it decayeth. And <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> ſayde: The fayre blacke was better accepted, then the fowle white: Meanyng the blacke man fayre condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and well nurtured, to be better than a bewtifull boy, fowly fedde, voyde of good behauiour.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Socrates,</hi> a ſchoolemaſter, had a Glaſſe in his Schoole, and euery day, hee cauſed his Schoolers to beholde their faces, ſaiyng to him that was fayre, ſée that thy bewtie bée allotted and allied to like conditions. If the face had been hardly fauoured, he wiſht him ſo to behaue himſelfe, that the puritie of mild manners, ſhould bewtifie and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne his euill fauourd viſage.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Glicon,</hi> luſtely limmed, pretely proportioned, conceaued ſutche pride therein, that he thought nature had forgot to moulde or make the like: forneying (ſommond by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie buſineſſe) through a craggie and roughe waye, his ſtately ſteede fell, and ſo martird his fine liuely limmes, that the worſte in the towne, felt &amp; taſted of more eaſe than hée. Than did he inueigh againſt pride, and his folly excéeding therin. By theſe examples, all may learne, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15694:13"/>nothinge is eternall, but Vertue: Beauty ſoone blowen away, properneſſe of parſonage preſently periſheth. Fond <hi>Adoleſcencie,</hi> ſhould therfore repoſe no credit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. As for ritches and wealth, who would brag of them? which <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, be not worthie to bee the handmayde of Vertue.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Creſus,</hi> Kinge of the <hi>Lidianes,</hi> was exceedingly ritche, but quickly quailed with pinching pouertie.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thales</hi> the Philoſopher, was demaunded what was beſt for younge men to learne? He anſwered, that which they may bee commended for, and honoured in age: mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge Vertue and probitie of manners.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Plato</hi> had this Poſie, paynted vpon the Schoole wall: <hi>Happy is hee whom others harmes doo make to beware:</hi> And all his aſſembly of Schollers, ſhould reade it duely and daily, to the intente, that they ſéeing others executed for lyinge, Fornication, Adultery, and other cryminall offences, might in reading the ſame, reforme themſelues. Finding by reading, the <hi>Romanes</hi> to be ſtudious of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and carefull of rude Adoleſcencie, I finde that theſe youthes of theſe yeares, ſhould be brought to the Market and there ſhould ſee the vertuous honoured, and the vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous puniſhed, to encourage them to labour for vertue.</p>
                        <p>The highe renowmed <hi>Hercules</hi> in his ſpring of yeares and manly might: beeinge brought to open aſſembly, to ſée the royall rewarde of honeſt liuers, perſwaded him ſelfe to doo thereafter, as <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth of him: and in time came ſo noble, that at this daye hee is not forgotten. Parentes ought to ſhew vnto their children, the ſtate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſtocke, and how long it was boulſtered out with Vertue: and that like wiſe it muſt bée vpholden by them: as wée reade of <hi>Eneas,</hi> in the 12. of the <hi>Eneidos,</hi> to haue wiſht his ſonne <hi>Aſcanius,</hi> to learne vertue of him, and fortune of others: And if hée bee baſe of byrth, yea, the heyre of a Donge Carte, his Parentes may ſhewe, how many poore Peiſantes and children, came by vertue to high honour and dignitie. As <hi>Dauid,</hi> from a Shepheard
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15694:14"/>to bee a kynge, with many others. They muſt follow Vertue, as <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith, in his Epittle: <hi>I bone quo virtus tua te ducit in pede fauſto.</hi> Laſtly, let prayſe for well doing be geuen them. For <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith: The minde of man to be mutche mooued thereby, and deſirous thereof.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ouid,</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>De triſtibus,</hi> ſaith: Prayſe to yéeld no ſmale force, to ſpurre a man to goodneſſe. <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi> and many others, be of the ſame opinion: therefore as due, dedicate it to them.</p>
                        <p>As farre as knowledge will geue mee leaue, I will decipher theyr duties, dieted to them by the vertuous forerunners, as foloweth:</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero</hi> aſcribeth to them for a dutie, to obey theyr elders: graye heares muſt bée honoured.</p>
                        <p>Secondlye, to chuſe a vertuous Regimente of life, and trimme trade of liuynge: as <hi>Hercules</hi> did after the <hi>Roman</hi> faſhion. Thirdely, to forget all childiſhneſſe, and vanitie, remembryng his ſtate, and that lewde behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, doeth not only annoy him, but alſo his freendes and folowers.</p>
                        <p>The firſt age is Virilitie, in Latten called vir: to the whiche worde addinge a ſillable tus, Vertue is denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated: as of <hi>Vir,</hi> Vertue. In this age, Vertue muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde, for yeres yelde courage: the minde is fit to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out Vertue. In this age, man muſt be fully clothed with the habite of Vertue, as Prudence, Iuſtice, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and Fortitude. Prudence, to inſtructe him to ſeaſon his ſpeeche there with, to recorde déedes doone: to diſpoſe preſent affayres, &amp; to ſuruey prudently all his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe in his vocation, to commendable ende. For it is the parte of an vndeſeréete man to ſay, I had not wiſt: or to prooue a <hi>Troian</hi> wiſe, too late.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Terence</hi> ſaith in <hi>Adelph.</hi> It is a poincte of wiſdom, not to looke to preſent, but to foreſee future caſualties. Iuſtice ſhal ſchoole him to pacience, concorde, humanitie, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealyng, the grounde of Vertues.</p>
                        <p>Temperance to obſerue a meane in all enterpriſes, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15694:14"/>modeſtie and chaſtitie.</p>
                        <p>Fortitude, not of body, but of couragious minde and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaunt ſtout ſtomacke, to countenance forth the fury and fiercenes of fawning fortune, with a goodly grace beeing pittifully pinched with pouerty: &amp; eſpecially to kepe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote wicked wrath, &amp; odious indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mad mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mindes, with rules of reaſon: <hi>Plato</hi> adiudged him moſt valiaunte, that coulde gouerne him ſelfe ſpurred to anger.</p>
                        <p>The laſt Caueat and rule, rated for virilitie, is ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue him ſelfe, as he wiſheth to bée eſtéemed of, &amp; accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to labour to leade his life in loyall league of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtye, hatinge acceſſe to the hatefull hue, that dighteth man with dire defame, and ſpiteful ſpots of ſtayned ſtem of liuing.</p>
                        <p>Olde Age béeing the ſixt, and laſt leaue taking, for the excellent experience and trim tryall had in expired lot of life, muſt be ſo furniſhed with the guiding gouernaunce of Prudence, that they ſo compaſſe all and ſinguler their affaires, in ſuch wiſe and ſubtill forte, as younge impes, may be inſtructed therwith.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero</hi> reporteth, that olde men in his dayes, were ſo expert and ſkilful in the common wealth, that the guided and gouerned the ſame, without any cauſe of ſtrife, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Warre.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Romulus,</hi> the bountifull builder of <hi>Rome,</hi> choſe an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth olde Fathers, whom of <hi>Senectus</hi> he called Senates, to rule the ſame: that their chriſtall like lyuinge, might bee an excellent example of prooued probitie to the youth thereof: and they as Princely pictures, and Images of honourable honeſty, had highted homage of ſurueyinge the ſame. And although they knew this yrkeſome age to bee rotten ripe, to ſeaſon and dounge the ground, yet leaſt the nature of man inthraled to the ſoueraignties of ſubtill Sathan, ſhoulde bee blinded therewith: they had ꝓrotrahed vppon their Iudiciall Seates, this Poſie.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="82" facs="tcp:15694:15"/>Remember man that thou art but duſt, &amp; daily draweſt on thertoo: Further, there was an olde withered wretch paynted, reſemblinge theſe bendinge backes to imbrace their Mother the ground, ready to the graue, that behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge it, they might not chooſe but execute Iuſtice aright.</p>
                        <p>The view of olde age, kept them backe from pinching the poore, or iniuringe their Neighbours: they followed <hi>Horace</hi> his good aduice, for deprauinge them ſelues of worldly bliſſe, they gyrded them to their Graues, daily expecting the onſet of dolefull Death.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>What decencie is due to God, and honeſtie towardes all men Chap. 4.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He true tutche of Vertue doth not conſiſt in the knowledge and ſcience therof: but in exhibiting the ſame, to reclaime the retchleſſe, or rather the graceleſſe Groomes, that flowriſh the Flag of Vices, and ſinne: And <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, in dooinge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, which maintayneth the ſtay and ſtate therof: Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge therefore, that the excellent eſſence, and beautifull béeing of vigent Vertue, conſiſteth in action, and daily déede of honeſty: I will ſhew how the actes of man haue their courſe, or ought to bee directed towardes God and man, and euery ſortes of people.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Vertuous obeyſance towardes God.</head>
                        <p>HOneſty towards God, martired for the wicked tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of ſpightful meaning man, cruelly crucified, rufully racked, lotheſomly laſhed with ſtinginge ſtripes, by lewde forlorne ſinners, conſiſteth in prayer, and pietie towardes his perſonage, in humble inthralment to his mercy, crauinge at his handes, to waſhe and mundiſes with the Well water of meare mercy, our ſoule ſoncke by reaſon of the fraight of ſinne, and ſurge of ſorrowes, to the pit of Perdicion, and gapinge gulfe of dread, and dampnation. To requeſt with trickling teares, as <hi>Dauid</hi>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15694:15"/>did, that hee of his benignant beautie, will rid vs of that heauy heritage and duetie due by our rufull race, runned from the ſtocke of <hi>Adam.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his thirde Booke, aſcribeth vs a ſeconde duetie, or ſeruice towardes our Sauiour: That is, to bée feruent in his cauſe, reuealers of true Religion, and pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhers of practiced pietie: For this onely cauſe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to God, were wee borne and created: was learning inuented, and all things faſhioned and framed of Chriſt? In this is wiſedome, as <hi>Liuie,</hi> and <hi>Valerius</hi> witneſſeth: and as <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth, and all other thinges vayne and tranſitorious.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>¶ Our dutie towardes man.</head>
                        <p>CHriſte in his Goſpell ſaith: <hi>Loue the Lorde thy God, and thy Neyghbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> By which we learne, that the firſt duetie is to him wards: The ſecond towards mankinde.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Lactantius</hi> liſtning to the wordes of the Goſpell, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the firſt function of Iuſtice, to be due to God, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to man: which beeinge ſo, if a man waxe cruell to his Brother, or tirannouſly tire him with vexacions, greefes, or other anxieties of minde: let him perſwade him ſelfe, to bee forſaken of God his Sauiour, and to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorne in the daungerous Denne of Dampnation: leaſt wee ſhould be ignoraunt of our duetie, <hi>Paule</hi> that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pearle of the Church, and poſting Preacher of God, ſheweth that wée muſt cloath the naked, harbor the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, bury the dead, féede the hungrie, viſite captiues with comfort, giue drinke to the tirſtie: which forrun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of fayth, bringeth bliſſe to the faithful ſoule of man. In dooing theſe thinges, wee ſhould prooue our ſelues ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Gods, kinde and curteous, amorous fortherers of firme and faſt fréendſhip one to another: abhorring fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, brawlinge, ſpite, enuie, mallice, as prouokers of death, and frying in the Fornace of Sathan.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15694:16"/>
                        <head>Towardes our natiue Countrey.</head>
                        <p>PHilolius in his fourth Booke affirmeth, that the olde Philoſophers did ſet more by their natiue ſoyle, than by their Parentes: Therfore <hi>Plato</hi> ſayd, that our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey chalengeth part of our life: for we are borne to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite the ſame, and that fiue wayes.</p>
                        <p>The firſt in trauelling for the honour and ryal renowne of the ſame: The inſtinct and inclination of nature fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth the ſame. For if wee come in place where our Countrey is defaced by twatlinge mates, or detected of crime: Nature aduerſant to ſuch aſſertions, wil boyle in man, and the freſh floiſh of blood, appearinge in mooued moode, will bewray the ſame, and cauſe conflictes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as often times it hath beene knowen, the like acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes to come to paſſe.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, in inſtructing the ſame with politicke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, which I take to be addicted, as perticuler function to Preachers, who of nature ought to labour therein, for that their fréendes and Fathers, be inhabitantes therin.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly to profit the ſame, by worde and deede to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it from bondage and captiuitie.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, to defend the ſame with maine force, and to repell all violence and iniury offered thertoo.</p>
                        <p>Laſtly, to dye for the honour of thy Countrey, as there are many of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and others Chronicled in <hi>Liuie</hi> at this day, for the doughty defence, and ſacrificed blood, in the behalfe of their natiue Lande, and that cauſed <hi>Horace</hi> to ſay: It is a méete thing tody for our Countrey: Why are valiaunt Captaines honoured? but that they be prompt, to hazard life and limmes, in the defence of their Countrey: as Sir <hi>William Drurie,</hi> who manfully raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the long beſéeged Caſtell of <hi>Edenborughe</hi> of his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhood, an acte worthy highted honour, and perpetuall praiſe: Captaine <hi>Morgan,</hi> Captaine <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Captaine <hi>Barkley,</hi> Captaine <hi>Frobuſher,</hi> with many other worthy Engliſh Captaines, and valiaunt Gentlemen that liue in flouriſhing fame, who ſo valianntly in forraine Landes, finiſhed their conflictes and bloody broyles, that for ſeare
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15694:16"/>of their manhood, from time to time, forraine enemies haue ſainted to molleſt Englande with warres. Who hath not harde of the hardy enterpriſe of famous <hi>Frobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher,</hi> and his fortunate company, who haue by their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell inritched this Lande, and Countrey.</p>
                        <p>Theſe and many ſuch others, worthy warriours, ſet more by fame and immortallitie of commendacion, then fumbling feare, and loſſe of lyfe: By ſuch came the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerbe: <hi>It is better to dye with honour, than to liue with ſhame.</hi> Such (I ſay) bee the gay Gardes of Englande, their Countrey, beeing worthy members therof. By the ayde of theſe, the Churles ſweate and frie at the fier, taſting of eaſe, when they fréeſe with froſt, and chilling colde, in daunger of death. As <hi>Tullie</hi> ſayde, that <hi>Rome</hi> was happy to haue ſuch a conſull as hee was: ſo maye Englande reioyce to haue procreated ſuch valiaunt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, to ſerue ſo good and gracious a Prince, as cauſe and occaſion, at any time doth require.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Dutie due to our Parentes.</head>
                        <p>WEe are not onely admoniſhed by prophane writers, to féede the humors of of our Parentes, but by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture and laſt true Teſtament of our Sauiour Chriſt, and ther in not onely in rated Law, ſet foorth by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> the meſſenger of Ieſus Chriſt, but in places de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon the performable promiſes of Chriſt Ieſn, and his meare mercy. Wherfore, who voyde of grace, gréeuouſly graueleth his Parentes, is not dampned to die the ſecond death (onely) by the Law of the Lord: but is indangered of the fruition of his manifolde mercy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the ſéede of <hi>Adam.</hi> And as the children be bound to obey, and doo as dutie defineth to them, ſo Parentes muſt not will, but ſuch thinges as be honeſt, vertuous, and lawfull and conſonant to the word of God: For wee muſt leaue father &amp; mother, and cléeue vnto the Lord, we read of many ſooliſh fathers, who béeinge enemies to the Croſſe &amp; Goſpell of Chriſt, at the houre of death, mooued vpon their bleſſinges, that their children ſhould perſiſt therin, a wicked and deteſtable decree of Parentes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15694:17"/>Parents ought not to commaunde their children, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge but that, whiche is honeſt, godly, and fit for their yeres and calling. And in ſutche, God commaundeth vs to be ſeruiceable at their neede, in worde, in deede, to cure their care to lay, to reléeue them preſſed with pouertie: and to beehaue our ſelues to adorne their callynge, and qualities, by our excellencie of liuynge, that their dulled humours, may be indulged by vs, and not impaired: that they may glory in vs, and not lothe vs: that they may ioy in our preſence, and not wiſh our abſence, or diſſolution of life. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, what is pietie and godlineſſe, but obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our parentes?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Philellius</hi> writyng of the duties of children towardes their parents, ſaieth: although we can neuer repaye like curteſies, and beſtowe vpon them, matchable benignant benefits: yet children muſt indeuour as farre as lieth in them, to regratifie them, as in ſeruyng, folowyng, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyng with them, in executing their willes, in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and performance: and if they commaunde thinges vnlawfull, vngodly, and vndecent: not to ſnarre or ſnap, quippe or carpe them for it: but modeſtly to perſwade them, to the contrarie, with reformable termes, or to let it ſlippe, it paſſing with patience.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>¶ Of ſutche pnniſhments as were appointed for vnobedient children.</head>
                        <p>IT will not only decipher the loſſe of longe life promiſed by God, in his commaundements, by ſhamefull death: for diſobedience perpatred towards our parents: whiche may ſufficiently, reclayme vs therefro: but I will adde how odious a thynge it was adiudged, amonge the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Inſidels, to miſcarie towardes them. <hi>Oreſtes Grecus,</hi> for killynge of his Mother <hi>Clitemneſtra,</hi> was chaunged into a féende or furious vgly Monſter: <hi>Nero</hi> was for the like déede doyng, counted a terrible Tyrant, worſe than bruite beaſtes: for the <hi>Storke</hi> beyng a brutiſh
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15694:17"/>and ſenceleſſe birde, wil féene her Dam and progenitors, ouer egged and worne with age. Amonge the <hi>Romanes,</hi> bée that moleſted his Parentes, or payned them to death, was wretchedly wrapped in a Bulles ſkinne, aſſociated with a Serpent, and throwen into the deapth of the Sea.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Duties towardes their Schoolemaiſters.</head>
                        <p>IVuenall a Poet, pregnant of wit, peereleſſe for paſſing pleaſanntneſſe of Phraſe, and Methode of Writinge, ſayth in his <hi>Satyres,</hi> that many honoured their Maiſters and teachers, as they did their Parentes: for as proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors giue by Gods ayde, bodily beeing, ſo teachers the liuely life of the minde, garniſhed with the garde and company of vertues, beautified with mildenes of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and nurture. And truly if wée had nothingels, but fleſh and bones, which wee haue by benefit of Parentes, wee ſhould prooue inferior to ſenceleſſe creatures: for what is it but the ſincke of ſinne, and open ſepulchre and graue of greefes, without inſtruction and inſtitutions of a Teacher? Wherfore next to Parentes, I finde them to bee reue renced of olde time, though now a dayes pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhly paltred withall.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Philelius</hi> commendeth obedience, &amp; reuerence towards their Inſtructors, as a meane to obtaine Learning, and he explaineth it by the example of <hi>Troianus,</hi> the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who in all poinctes highly honoured his teacher.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in ſo much that beeinge Emperour hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred him before him, in all places.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Marcus Antonius, a Romane</hi> péere, ſo honoured his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors, that beeing deade, hee had their Images made of gliſteringe Golde, and erected in his Cubickle and Chamber.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero,</hi> the Father of fine Phraſe, and fluent ſpéeche, maketh mencion in euery of his Bookes, of his Maiſters, and furtherers in Learninge.</p>
                        <p>Theſe men knew what learning was, &amp; what benefit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15694:18"/>there was by it atchiued: but hammer headed horders of money, ſet more by a penny, than by the excellency of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Artes and Sciences. To caſt Pearles amonge Swine is plaine pittie, and not loyall liberalitie: I will compare them to <hi>Eſopes</hi> Cocke, who in the Dounghill found a precious Pearle: hée looked vpon it, ſaw it cleare and bright, yet knew not the precious vſe, and vallure thereof: Oh (ſayth hée) I had rather haue one grayne of Barley, or other corne, than a buſhell of theſe bright ſtones. So it fareth with the Countrey clownes, they had rather ſaue a penny, then profit their Children in learning: the reaſon is, becauſe they know not how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent it is, and that a man without learninge is an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of death.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Of thoſe which contempned their Maiſters and teachers.</head>
                        <p>WIcked <hi>Nero,</hi> whoſe diueliſh deede to his Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, condempneth for a reprobate and abiecte, is noted of all writers of ingratitude towards his Maiſter: for hee was the death of <hi>Seneca</hi> his Teacher: that lewds lob and diſſolute Tirantt, bad him chuſe his death: hee tooke a Pen knife and launced all the vaynes of his body, and ſo killed him ſelfe as his name ſoundeth, for <hi>Senecaus</hi> is his name, that is ſlayinge him ſelfe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Beroaldus</hi> in prouerbiall diſcourſe, inueyinge againſt the tiranny of wicked <hi>Nero,</hi> ſayth: hee is to bee ſpitted and ſpited at, that will infame his teacher, or Maiſter: they fret and fume, chide and chafe, to pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite their Schollers, wherfore of right they may require, and of dutie, demaund furtherance at their handes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Duties towardes ourfreendes.</head>
                        <p>EXperience hauing taught mee, that very fréendes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied by nature, &amp; adoption for curteous behaniour, to haue ſallen at debate, and with dint of beyſlerens blooddy
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15694:18"/>blowes, to haue cleane battered the Forte of fréend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe and Bulwarkes of profeſſed amitie: I thinke and ſuppoſe that fury, to haue yſſued of ignorance, and lacke of duetie allotted to the profeſſed vertue, to exile ſuch falſhood in fellowſhip and bloody bickermentes, I wil ſhew how they harboring in the Hauen of Amitie, may eſcape the ſurge and Sirtes of Diſſenſion, and for the maintaynance of the loyall league of true loue, let them obſerue ſixe principall preceptes.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, doo not exigate or demaund, at thy aſſociate in louing league, any vnhoneſt exployte, or perpetrate and commit a deede of naughty demeanure, to cracke his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, or ſommon him ſhame.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, not like a fléeting Swallow, to accompany thy fréend in proſperitie, and to further a faire face of frendſhip: and in dule, and dire diſtreſſe, to ſuffer him to caſt the cardes of colde comfort alone. In the Sommer a man may haue the chirping chat of the ſwallow, but in Winter, compared to aduerſitie, ſhee vtterly forſaketh thee: Such bee flatterers, and not fréendes.</p>
                        <p>Thirdely, to will and nill all one thing, one ſtudie, one exerciſe, for <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth: diuerſitie of things, aſke diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of lyuinge.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, that wee doo not to our freend, but as wee woulde, hée ſhould doo to vs, for true and truſty freends: haue one minde, one harte in two bodies.</p>
                        <p>Fifthly, not to loue or beare a ſigne and ſhewe of freendſhip, in hope of happy rewarde: for wee ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gine, than to aſke.</p>
                        <p>Laſt of all, fréendly obeyſaunce, according to callinge, not as ſome, which becauſe they thinke a man to bee their freende, will preſume to robbe him of his honour, vpon which, ſpronge vp the Prouerbe: To much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie, breedeth a contempt: Such be not freendes but robbers of mans honour, and Theeues, hauinge the Cloake of freendſhippe on, vnder which, they ſteale a mannes worſhippe or callinge from him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15694:19"/>In the chuſing of a fréend in déede, wée muſt know him to bee of good conuerſation and behauiour, than wée muſt haue an eye to his manners, geſtures, and conueyances, and examine them, whither they bée ſufferable, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without grudge of conſcience, wee may tollerate them: els wee were better neuer to aſſociate our ſelues to ſuche a mate, for it will bée an occaſion of ſedition and anger: It is aduerſaunt to the rule of Fréendſhip, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thy adopted fréends, before a congregacion, or to giue him haſe termes inferior to his callinge, which may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſſe the like boldeneſſe in the hearers, to afforde thy fréend the like: and ſo thou ſhalt bee a means of lowtiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to him, whom thou ſeemeſt to loue: Finally, I muſt admoniſh fréendes not opprobriouſly to obiect kindeneſſe, tendered them in their aduerſitie, nor hauing imparted vpon them, ſome good turne to miſuſe the partye, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him bound to obey, for the receipt therof: which I haue noted in a froward fréend of mine. Such kindenes <hi>Cicero</hi> repineth againſt, ſaying: true fréendſhip abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from cauſe of diſſenſion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Dutie towardes olde age.</head>
                        <p>THe <hi>Romanes</hi> ſchooled in <hi>Cicero</hi> his trim tracte of due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, made a Law, that whoſoeuer paſſed by the elder ſorte of Cittizens, without obeyſance of Benet, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of bones, ſhould bee puniſhed by the head: which, as I conſter, to bee beheaded, or els to ſtand a ſhamefull A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathemat yoaked in Pillory, to the vtter cracke of their credite: Age is the crowne of honour, for that it is the Cheſte of prudente experience, and ſuppoſition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, els had hee beene cut off before hee had attayned thereto.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayth, that they are to be borne withal, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of age, &amp; aboundance of choller, collected through the want of naturall heate, to diſgeſt humors heaped in their cruſhed carcaſſes. And for that the ſtate of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15694:19"/>common Wealth is, and hath euer beene, committed to their diſcreete rule and gouernance: not only prophane Authors aſcribe them duetifull reuerence, but it is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in Scriptures, that wée might more reuerently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh and performe the ſame.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Towardes Matrones and Women.</head>
                        <p>I Am not ignorant, that dowltiſh dottrels, haue ſpiteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſought to ſpoyle Women of their honour, inferring paltry proffers, to forder their furious frowardneſſe, and ſpite conceaued againſt them, out of canckered pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhe Poettes: which altogeather voyde of good nature, manifeſtly ſhew the mayme of nature, which ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly graueleth them, that they indeuour to inſinuate and flatter mankinde to forſake woman, the only ſolace, ioye, and Iewell of the world: Amonge whom, <hi>Albertus</hi> that malicious man, bewrayed their imperfection, more of ſpite, than of neceſſitie or thinge ſpectant to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of man: his beaſtlineſſe ſhall condempne him a Traitour to Women, and they the trimme treaſure of man: foule and fulſome, lewde &amp; lothſome is that beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly birde, which beſmerth his owne neaſt. What worde is ſo baſe? what terme ſo wicked? or name ſo odious, as may fit this forderer of miſcheefe to woman kinde, being his nuſted neaſt, and carefulleſt kindred.</p>
                        <p>O odious <hi>Albert,</hi> and you abiecte outcaſt kiſtrels, who forgettinge your byrth and beeinge, to haue depended of women, ryotouſly raue, and deſperatly deuiſe, vndiſcret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcouer their naturall imperſections: as though it lay in them to bee rid thereof. Recante yee ſilly cinicall ſectes, your eyes condempne your worke, your toungues at the view of beautifull daintie Diamondes, cry <hi>Pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus:</hi> Your Penne panteth for greefe, to haue inueyed againſt honeſt Matrones: yea, as ſhame of <hi>Albertus,</hi> his deede weynd him to woe, and miſery, ſo no (doubt) ſuch miſchéeuous ſearchers of maymes towardes their owne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15694:20"/>Mothers, ſhalbe diſmiſde with the like rewarde.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sainct Peter,</hi> a man of milder opiuion, ſaid: A woman to be a crowne of honour to a man: and to be borne with all as the weaker veſſell, and ſhould not extende crueltie towardes them, neither in worde, nor déede. For thers is no Tiger ſo terrible or fierce, no lion ſo lewde or cruel: no Beare ſo bare and voyde of gentileneſſe, or naturall clemencie, as to payne or pinche, gréeue or moleſt their pammes, mutche leſſe man, indued with reaſon. I can compare them to no creature, but to vipers which recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence their dammes which bare them, in gnawyng their guttes. Becauſe there be but few that ſo ſclander onſlie defame the ſtately ſtemne of women, the onely porte of the world, and ſure ſollace of man: I will bee take mee to ſcilence.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Dutie towards our enemies.</head>
                        <p>IT may ſéeme ſtraunge to the nature of man, ſo ſiercely geuen to reuenge, that any league or loyaltie, or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſhould be obſerued betwéen furious ſnes, or enemies Except he hath read it in Hiſtoriagraphers, who exhibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the gaze of mens bluddie broyles, and warlike tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions: in whiche is ſpecified the lawe of armes, how truce is concluded (eſtſoones) a certeine ſpace: which to violate or defile the corage and valiant ſtoute ſtomacke of venterous Captaynes, cannot be brought or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cicero</hi> affirmeth in his firſt booke of duties, that faith boluntarie plighted, and aduiſedly geuen, to our foes, is to bee obſerued, and parte performed, and in very déede, it is a poynt of brutiſh beaſtelineſſe, for to ſtrike without admoniſhion or caueate.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Terence</hi> ſayd, the wiſeman will demurre of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before hée fight. But Vertue admoniſheth vs, not to fight, but to bée armed with her handemayde, dame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but if Choller ſpurre thee to it, I thought good to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15694:20"/>ſhew how infierce dealynge wée muſt prooue men, and not beaſtes.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Liuie,</hi> the Marciaſiſt Poet ſaith: That wée ought not to fight but for Peace, and quietneſſe. And forgeuynge is the nobleſt reuenge that may bée. Men ought not to iarre or iangle for euerte triffle: for of ſufferaunce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth eaſe. And as the Engliſh man ſayeth: It is good ſlepynge in a whole ſkinne.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Dutie due to Straungers, or Traueilers.</head>
                        <p>DOughtie and dutifull <hi>Dido,</hi> Quéene of <hi>Carthage,</hi> to the inſtruction of people, how they ſhould entertaine ſtraungers, and tired trauelers: So feaſted <hi>Eneas,</hi> and his accompanied troupe of trimme <hi>Troianes,</hi> with dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie diet, and royal hoſpitalitie, that to this day her boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe towarde ſtraungers, is freſh and vigent, in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of men.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Virgill,</hi> thought it worthe the while, to Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in his booke ſo notable a facte, and to waſte his winde in deciphyring the manners thereof.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>Romans</hi> forwarde in good déedes and courteous conueiance, who indeuoured to prooue famous for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutynge vertuons actions, gaue and imparted the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Conſulſhippe vpon <hi>Torquinius:</hi> and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhippe to <hi>Numa Pompeius,</hi> béeyng ſtraungers: which argueth greate lenitie and force of Vertue, habitante in them.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Beroaldus,</hi> and <hi>Liuie</hi> affirme: that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was feared of ſutche, as miſcaried towarde poore Peregrines and ſtrayinge ſtraungers. And the Gentiles kepte hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie, conſecrated to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the reuenger of diſtoyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offered them.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Plautus</hi> in his Commedie called <hi>Paen.</hi> Reproueth one ſharꝑely for deridynge and ſcornyng of ſiraungers.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15694:21"/>
                           <hi>Plato</hi> pardoned no fault doone to them: the Scripture ſay: Hée is accurſt that leadeth the blinde, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraunger out of his way: but now they haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him <hi>Drummes</hi> intertainment, ſoone in at doores, and ſorier out: light come, light goe: None is ſo derided, mocked, and laughed at, as ſtraungers, now in England they bee puniſht, whipt, plagued, on euery ſide: there is no ſparks of <hi>Roman</hi> kindeneſſe in them, no whit of <hi>Dido</hi> his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe, byding in them: which is an occaſion of ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to this our natiue Soyle.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Duetie towardes our Mayſters, whom wee ſerue bound or free.</head>
                        <p>ALl that goe vnder the name of Seruauntes, muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe foure wayes, towardes their Maiſters, whom they daily feede vpon, and recreate their bodyes by their prouiſion, as well in nightfull reſte, as daylis dyet.</p>
                        <p>Firſt, it is ſpectant to the execution of ſeruile function, to bee preſt ready, and willing to finiſh the rated buſines of their Maiſters, not as Snayles, ſlowly ſettinge it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, but with couragious dilligence, delightinge therein.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, not glaueringe or flattering their Maiſters in their preſence, and in their abſence fraudilently to deceane them, a thing though it ſcape the chaſticement of man, yet it can not paſſe the iuſt reuengement of God, for hee hateth the wicked diſſemblinge man, and falſhood ſtinketh in his preſence, prouoking his déepe diſpleaſure.</p>
                        <p>The thirde, <hi>Plautus</hi> teacheth vs, ſayinge: a ſeruaunte muſt forſake and aboliſhe from his minde, all priuate gaine, and onely heede his Maiſters profit, and deale iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly therin.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly, to bee ſilent, when they bee mooued, though choller ſo blindeth them, that they ſwarue from the truth and not to anſwere, <hi>Quid pro quo,</hi> as their equals: and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15694:21"/>not to blab abroade their fables, talkes, or ſuruey in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſinge of matters, prouokinge their iuſt diſpleaſure, or lewdly luſt after their Wiues or Seruauntes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The laſt duety is towardes Magiſtrates and Officers.</head>
                        <p>MAgiſtrates and Officers, beeinge the liuely limmes and members of our gracious Quéene, and Godly Gouerneſſe, are dutifully to bée obeyed: for where there is no order, ſayth <hi>Oliuerus Carnaruonenſis,</hi> there is ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piternall horror, and pathe to perdition. In what doo wee differ from brutiſh beaſtes, but in order and lawfull league of life.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Liuie</hi> ſayth: if the armes, and feete, and other mans members, fal out with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head, they muſt all periſh: if the Subiectes contempne Magiſtrates, executioners of the Lawe, both Prince and Subiectes, muſt taſte the gale thereof. God ſende the breach of order bée not the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of England, and ſtubberneſſe againſt our Princes Lawes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Decency deuiſed to fit all ſeaſons.</head>
                        <p>TO aduaunce honeſtie, and ſhewe Dame Vertue to be fully famylied and habitant in vs, wee muſt haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte and conſideration of time and place: for if our talke be not conſonant to them both, it argueth litle lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge or hoped hap of Vertue: A learned and vertuous man (in deede) needeth no further commendacion, but to preſſe in place where hee may ſhew his actions allied to Vertue and knowledge, arguinge probitie of life, and perfect publiſhed manners.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Macrobius</hi> ſayth: the due obſeruation of time and place, to bee the ſureſt ſigne of wiſedome.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Pyttacus Mitillus,</hi> wiſheth a man before hée enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe any exployte, to conſider and pithily to perpende, to whom hee ſueth, what hee ſueth for, and when.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15694:22"/>As we reade of one <hi>Clobulus,</hi> who came to <hi>Caeſar</hi> inthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to wrathe, to requeſt admiſſion, to haue dominion in a Promontarie appertaining to his Empire: <hi>Caeſar</hi> fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at other loſſes, commaunded him to bee hanged, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: it is better to hange thee by the necke, than thou ſhouldeſt ſpoyle the Countrey, and ſpurre many thereto.</p>
                        <p>Thus it falleth out with ſuch, as deſire ſo daſieth, that they can not ſee, or to obſerue time fitting their purpoſe.</p>
                        <p>Hereupon <hi>Terence</hi> ſayde: I came in ſeaſon, which is the chéefeſt thinge of all. Which that it may the better bee heeded of children and others, I will ſpeake ſomwhat of.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>How to vſe thy ſelfe at a Banket.</head>
                        <p>AT Banckets or feaſtes, where multitude of men are reſembled, and towled to repaſt: haue conſideration of the Gueſtes, of their calling, wealth and honeſtie, and prefer not thy ſelfe, beefore them: If thou by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of aunceſtrie, Noble or Worſhipfull, and others lately loyalled with worſhip or honour in place: Diſdain them not, in poſſeſſinge the ſeate of Soueraignitie, for they exalted by their owne indeuor and vertue, be better than thou deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of nobilitie, beeing ignoble, degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from thy ſtately ſtacke. Euery man will take thée as they finde thee: placed to thy contentation, bable not of Scriptures, as meane Miniſters will, but follow ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the example of <hi>Socrates,</hi> a ſinguler Philoſopher, who requeſted to ſpeake at a Bancket: hee anſwered, I am not ſkilled in things fit for the place and ſeaſon, adiudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge Philoſophie vnworthy to bee vttered amonge Cup Goſſips, neither did it become his grauitie, to twatle of vanities or olde Wiues Tales, as ſome of higher pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion will doo. And if mirthe mooue thee to wade, and paſſe in pleaſure and ieſt: let it bée ſo handled, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downd to no mans diſcredit or grauell any gueſt inuited or bidden to the Bancket. For <hi>Anagiris</hi> ſaide, that a man is ſooner mooned to choller and anger, being occupied
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15694:22"/>in drinking and feaſtinge than other wiſe: which experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence explayneth daily, for drunken frayes bee common. Next, a man muſt ſo dyet his ſtomacke, that it belch not, nor boyle vp, as charged with ouerplus or gluttony, to annoy the hearers ſqueaſie ſtomackes, nor ply the Pot to often, drinkinge diſhonour to him and his: Neither is it méete for thee to common abroad priuate Fables, or tales tolde in thy preſence, for therby thou infameſt thy ſelfe, taken of them for a ſecret well meaning man.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Beroaldus</hi> ſaith, that the Gentiles celebratinge feaſtes, did ſhow the Threſhall to the gueſtes: wiſhing that what ſoeuer was doone or ſayd there, ſhould go no further.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Horace</hi> biddinge <hi>Torquatus</hi> to bancket with him, and his fréendes wiſhed him to bringe ſuch as they might bee merry: for in deede, it is no hartie mirthe, when a man maye not for feare vtter his minde, or leaſt it bee blazde abroad: which deare Reader, if it ſéeme odious vnto thee follow it the leſſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>How to vſe thy ſelfe in ſober company.</head>
                        <p>THe whole drift of Arts, and ſomme of ſwéete Science is, to know much, and to ſuruey his trade of lyuing ſo amonge men, that they may daily aſſociate them ſelues with him, to reape ſome benefit of his vertue, for attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of which lot of loyall life, wee muſt obſerue ſeauen poynctes. Firſt, to tollerate the fretting fits of men and manners, and to paſſe them with patience, and not barke at the ſhakinge of euery réede. Secondly, in boundes of bountie and honeſt lyfe, to will and nill with them, and to ſhun that loatheth them: &amp; labour for that, which get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth gaine to thée or them. Thirdly, in worde, déede and lyuing, wee reſemble the Methode and manner of their lyuinge, for than ſhalt thou bee partaker of the prayſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed them. Fourthly, not to take in dudgion any matter, without greate and approoued cauſe and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Fifthly, in humilitie and ſubmiſſion, to handle and deale with all men, dooinge to others, as thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt wiſhe them to doo towardes thee.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15694:23"/>Sixtly, to bee thankeful for curteſies taſted, which ſhal prouoke thy further gaine, and good will.</p>
                        <p>Laſtly, to ſpeake well of all men: Theſe thinges bee the Ladder to climbe into credit with the ſobreſt ſorte of men, which bee not enticed with vanitie, to wiſh the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of man, but onely with Vertue.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Obſeruations in mutuall talke or communicacion.</head>
                        <p>TAke héede thou dooſt not ouerthwart a man in his tale or interrupt him with an other, which argueth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection and want of manners in thée: Carpe not, nor iyebe not a man tellinge the ſomme of his meaninge, as thou couldeſt daſh him out of countenaunce: for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and gréeuouſeſt théeuery is, to rob a man of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie or countenance. Bée not an oppen accuſer of the common people, or coyner of lyes, and flyinge fables, and father them not vpon others, in thy talke had with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers priuatly, for thinking to hurte others, thou hurteſt thy ſelfe. Search not after the ſecreates of other men: for beeing reuealed vnto thee, they will animate thée, to doo him miſchéefe: and in hope of gaine and lewde lucre, or to bring him vnder feete, wil kindle thy wrath againſt him. And if the partie bee thy better, giue <hi>Diu garde,</hi> ſalutation fittinge his callinge, els may bee take it for a mockery: &amp; before a Noble man or Magiſtrate, ſo frame the ſtate of thy body, that you ſtand vpright, not reelinge this way nor that way, not ytching, nor rubbinge, nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouringe on legge, more one than another, not bytinge or ſmacking thy lippes, not ſcratching thy head, nor pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge thy eares, not lowringe in lookes, nor glauncinge thine eyes too and fro, not ſad nor fierce, but meeke and merry, ſhowinge good diſpoſition and nature, to bee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant and graciouſly grafted in thee.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>In iourneyinge.</head>
                        <p>WHat callinge ſo euer a man bee, high or low, myrth will become him well, in trauell, ſo it bee good and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15694:23"/>honeſt: for a merrye wayfaringe mate, is as good as a Weyne or Charret: but take heede your mirth reache not to ſcorne ſuch as meete with you, or to any man his hurte or daunger: but refreſh your ſelues with Stories and merry tales, inuented to exile the languor of limmes and ſtifneſſe of tyred members.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Cato</hi> giueth this edicte and commaundement to traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to ſalute gently ſuch as méete you, not iuſtling them into the mire, or grauelling them with miſdemeanure.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Of Time.</head>
                        <p>AS all thinges are not fit for euery man, ſo bee they not decent for all ſeaſons: for ieſtinge Spirites, bee not accepted amonge mourners or ſobbinge Sainctes: neyther is the ſad Sot or meagre mooued man, eſteemed among ſuch as ſet Coppe on Hoope: wherfore it is perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the polliticke perſon, to chaunge his coate as the company doo: But the royall rules of famous Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy do inſtructe vs to vſe a meane, the Methode &amp; ſomme of my booke, for in proſperity lofted by fawning Fortune we ought to perpend &amp; conſider, that after much drouth &amp; faire weather, foloweth raine with tempeſtuous change: &amp; eftſoones, the minde is drowned with the enchaunting dalyinge delightes of fawninge Fortune, that the partie can not ſee time to prayſe God. Wherupon was it ſaid: <hi>It is eaſier for a Cammell to goe through the eye of a Nedle, than for a ritche man to goe or aſcend to the highe preſence of God:</hi> And it planteth in the plat of Secrecie, Pompe and Pryde, to diſdayne ſuch as bee preſſed with pouerty, and gloriouſly to crow ouer their heades.</p>
                        <p>In aduerſitie, a tymorous time, and heauie happes of ſilly man, wee haue to follow valiaunte <hi>Eneas</hi> example, who toſſed in vnknowen Coaſtes, in daungers of <hi>Sirtes</hi> in ſurging Seas, bitterly bayted by ſpitefull Fortune, to the great recreation of fayntinge fellowes, ſayde: God will ende theſe ſorrowes. So man muſt hope wel, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15694:24"/>though it bee the Key of Deſperation: yet a bliſful blaſt and gladſome gale, will deliuer the hardy harte from gulphe of gaule and ſorrow. Surely, patiencie paſſeth, and is the beſt Buckler a man can haue. Therfore to ende, take time as time is, countenaunce thy ſelfe to time: let it bee thy trimme Tayler, to ſhape thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce in all places.</p>
                        <p>NOw (gentle Reader) I will adde three Poinctes, the conſeruatiues of Vertue.</p>
                        <p>Alwayes accept of Vertue, and Honeſty.</p>
                        <p>Doo nothing that thou doubteſt of.</p>
                        <p>Doo not accompany nor aſſociat thy ſelfe to the wilful: Which if thou obſerue, it wil ſo (perhappes) lighten thee to the Pathe of Vertue, that not onely here thou ſhalt bée accepted, but in the preſence of GOD, to whom bee all prayſe and honour for euer. Amen.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15694:24"/>
                  <head>A Pithie Epiſtle and learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, of the worthineſſe of honourable VVed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, ſent written (as a Iuell) vnto a worthie Gentlewoman, in the time of her widowhoode, to direct and guide her in the new election of her ſeconde huſbande, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F God (whiche is the</hi> only giuer of all good things, had endewed me with the diuine gift of ſo greate eloquence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I might without any reprehenſion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with that worthie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Grecian <hi>Pericles,</hi> whoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred vaine of filed eloquence was ſo excellent: whoſe pronunciacion and vtterance was ſo pleaſant: whoſe words and ſentences were ſo ponderous and vehement, that in perſwading and diſſwadynge, hee had ſo greate and wonderfull grace, that all men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herde him, gaue their whole conſente vnto him: in ſo mutche, that many learned clarkes of greate renowne, haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of him, that he did vſe ſo excellently, and with ſuch wonderful force, to fulminate and thunder out his words and ſentences, that for his ſurpaſſyng grace and marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous facilitie in perſwadynge, no man was euer yet able therein to matche with him: If now my barren ſkill, were fully comparable with the greate cunning and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſynge knowledge of this worthy <hi>Pericles,</hi> yet here I fréely confeſſe, I ſhould appere mutche more barbarous, then the rude and groſſe <hi>Garamantes,</hi> if I ſhould take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, to ſet forthe the dignitie of honorable wedlocke, and holy Matrimonie, accordynge to the deſertes thereof, or go aboute to paint it out with ſutch high commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as it hath alwayes béen thought worthy of, euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſte thoſe that haue moſte flowriſhed with pregnant wittes, and haue excelled withall kinde of knowledge, hothe Diuine and humane.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15694:25"/>But though I am not able, according to the worthines therof, to intreat of it, nor to ſet forth the worthy effectes and fruites of the ſame, accordinge to my wiſhed deſire: yet wil I ſhew my minde and determinate purpoſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, according to the dutiful honour and reuerence I beare vnto the deſerued dignitie of it.</p>
                  <p>Let other prayſe Chaſtitie ſo mutch as they liſt, which (they ſay) filleth Heauen: (I pray God it doo ſo) yet wil I commende Matrimonie, whiche (I am ſure) repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth and filleth bothe Heauen and Earthe.</p>
                  <p>Let other ſet foorthe ſingle life, with ſo many praiſes as they can heape and tumble one in an others necke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (they ſay) it is voyde of all careful trouble and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe: Yet will I for euermore commende the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſtate of honorable wedlocke, which refuſeth no kinde of payne and trouble, ſo that it may brynge any profit at all to the publike weale of Chriſtendome.</p>
                  <p>Let other prayſe that kinde of life, whereby mankynde decayeth, and in proceſſe of time ſhoulde bée vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: Yet will I commend that manner of life, which begetteth and bringeth forthe, excellent Kynges, noble Princes, princely Dukes, puiſſant Lordes, valiant Kni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes, worthie Gentlemen, conning Artificers, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the common weale, and learned wittes, to gouerne the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Let others aduance that life, whereby Monarchies, Empyres, and Kyngedomes, are made deſolate, barren, and vnfrutefull: Yet will I moſte of all prayſe that life, whiche maketh Realmes to flowriſh with innumerable thouſandes of people, wherby the Publique weale is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in ſafe eſtate. And what thing can there be more neceſſary then Matrimony, which concerneth the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of mans lyfe, the flower of perfite fréendſhip, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion of Realmes, the glorye of Princes, and that which is greateſt, it cauſeth immortalitie? Can chriſtian Matrimony bee any otherwiſe then a thinge of great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, and incomparable dignitie, ſéeing it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15694:25"/>neither of that auncient <hi>Mynos</hi> kynge of <hi>Crete,</hi> nor of <hi>Licurgus,</hi> the law maker of <hi>Lacedemonia:</hi> nor yet of <hi>Solon</hi> the ſage &amp; wiſe <hi>Athenian,</hi> but of the moſt highe and immortall God himſelfe, and by him alone commended vnto mankinde, in ſo mutche that men may ſéeme to bée allured, mooued and ſtirred vnto this ſtate of liuynge, by a certayne inſpiration of the holie ghoſte? In Paradiſe alſo that Garden of pleaſure was it inſtituted, yea, and that before any ſinne rayned in this worlde, to ſhew that it bringeth vnto man, greate ioye, wealthe, felicitie, and quietneſſe: and euer ſince that time hath it béen had in greate eſtimation, not only amonge them that profeſſe vnfained faith in the liuyng God, but alſo amonge ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as were led by the only inſtinct of nature: in ſo much, that it hath béen alwaies recounted a thinge of mutch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie and reproche, to liue without the eſtate of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke. It is manifeſt by the reporte of hyſtories, of how great eſtimation holy Wedlocke hath béen, euer ſince the firſt beginnyng of the world, among al degrées of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
                  <p>Who will not commende honorable Wedlocke, as a thynge of greate excellencie? Who will not thynke it a ſtate of liuinge worthie high prayſe and commendation? Yea, who will not iudge that it ought to bee embraced with méetyng and folded armes, ſeyng that by it, ſo many notable treaſures do happen vnto vs? Vertue is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, Vice is eſchewed, howſes are repleniſhed, Cities are inhabited, the grounde is tilled, Sciences are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Kyngdomes floriſhe, Amitie is preſerued, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like weale is defended, naturall ſucceſſion is continued, good Artes are taught, honeſt order is kept, Chriſtendom is enlarged, Goddes word<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan>e is promoted, the conſience is quieted, lewde life is auoyded, and the glory of God is highly aduaunced and ſet forthe? And who euer wanted, that liued accordyng to Gods worde in Chriſtian Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie? God leaueth none ſuccourleſſe that put their truſt in him. Did not Chriſte turne the water into ſweete Wyne at a certayne Mariage in <hi>Cana,</hi> to ſhew that as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15694:26"/>many as liue in holy matrimonie accordinge to his word ſhall neuer wante? The water of the Riuer, ſhall ſooner bee turned into wine, and the ſtones of the ſtreete into breade, then the faithfull ſhall lacke or be founde ſuccour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Did not God feede the people of Iſraell with meat from he auen? did he not giue them drinke out of the hard rocke? Did hee not make a Crowe to bring meate to the Prophete <hi>Elyas,</hi> &amp; ſo wonderfully fedde him twiſe a day? Euen ſo will he do with vs, if we be faithfull, and ſéeke to liue according to his worde. <hi>The bleſſyng of God maketh men riche</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi>) <hi>The ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feareth God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>al the time of his life, ſheweth mercy vnto the poore, and lendeth vnto them that haue neede, &amp; yet hath he gods plentie and enough for his children that ſuccede him.</hi> Theſe goodly properties and fruitfull effectes, theſe manyfolds commodities and ſpeciall greate benefites, theſe diuine bleſſynges &amp; wonderfull graces, beſides an iufinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber more treaſures then I am able here to recite, whichs ſpryng out of holy and chriſtian Matrimonie, me thinks are able and ſufficient inough, to encourage and win all kinde of perſons, bothe men and women, widowes, and widowars, batchelers, and maydens, willingely to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and take vpon them the comfortable eſtate of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable wedlocke.</p>
                  <p>wherfore (good coſen) hauyng now troubled you thus farre with a rude diſcourſe of wedlocke, whereof I know well you haue had a more certaine and perfit proofe, then I am able by pen to painte foorth, becauſe you haue béen a wedded woman a longe and happie time, &amp; haue enioyed the bleſſed benifit of ſo good a huſband, as by him I doubt not but you haue had the full experience, aſwell of theſe manifolde felicities and greate commodities by me reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as of many other mo ſurpaſſyng treaſures, whiche happen to faithfull married couples, not able by me to be expreſſed, by reaſon I neuer taſted yet the happy bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of honorable wedlocke: I wil now haſten towardes other matter, and ceaſe to procéede any further in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15694:26"/>of this high degree of holy matrimony: whoſe worthie excellencie, doth more ſufficiently ſet foorth and commend it ſelf, then my inuencion is able to deuiſe. And whereas (good coſen) in this mine attempte, I may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be thought ſomewhat bold, to trouble you with this longe and tedious treatiſe in writing, yet if it wil pleaſe you to thinke wel of mine enterpriſe, and peruſe it ouer with good aduiſement, I truſt you ſhall finde the matter ſutche, as all your labour ſhal not be loſt, though the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion be founde but ſimple. It is only good will &amp; chriſtian charitie (my beloued Coſen) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath enforced me to frame my pen thus muche to trouble you, wherin I beſéeke you to pardon my boldeneſſe, and to take in good part my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple entente. The curious cooke doth dight y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rude morſell with ſome conceit of his cunning, but I haue no other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or ſauce of ſauour to grace my ſimple diſh withal, but the neuer vading and euer growyng grayne of good will, which I beſéeke you to take in good parte, &amp; to accept this ſimple inuention, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfit pledge thereof, growyng out of mine owne barren grounde, no far fet thinge, neither déerely bought, and therfore perchance not méete for you, eſpecially if you be very lady fine: it is no greater then came out of mine owne pen, no more precious, then may be kept and caried in a few leaues of paper, of no further forme &amp; faſhion, then mine owne hands could frame, of no better inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine owne ſimple wit might deuiſe: wherfore as you ſée, ſo ſhal you taſte: &amp; as you like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, ſo accept my preſent. I thought it my part (if it wil pleaſe you to take it wel) not to ſpare pen, paper nor pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in writing vnto you. And though it were more méete for mee, to treate of trifles, then miſteries, thinges of ſmale force, then matters of waight &amp; great importance, yet conſidering your perſon, whoſe caſe requireth euen in enforced trifles to ſéeke a grauitie, &amp; beinge lothe that loſte labour ſhould runne with loſte time (for loſt time I accounte loſte landes) I beethought my ſelfe to deuiſe ſome matter, that happely mighte quite your laboure in Readyng, and not to bee altogether fruteleſſe for wit:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15694:27"/>ſo that my wordes might not altogether ſéeme as waſted winde, but that I might be ſomewhat better occupied, then as one that did but tell the clockes, and watche the Sunne how he ſhadoweth the Diall. Conſideryng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the ſtate of your life, the caſe wherin you now ſtand, that is, towarde the worlde: A woman once a wife, now a wydow: And therfore hauyng of God, leaue and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by mariage to become a wife agayne: for when the huſbande is deade, the woman may lawfully betake her ſelfe vnto another, as Sainct <hi>Paule</hi> reporteth to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians:</hi> This your caſe I haue ſo mutch thought vpon, that I may not like a careleſſe ſtranger ſtande dombe, but as a carefull and faithfull well willer, open my mouthe, and vtter my minde vnto you, not that I meane in haſtie ſorte to perſwade you to Mariage, any otherwiſe then your owne wiſedome with good aduiſement ſhall thinke conuenient, for therin you may beſt be your owne iudge, for you know beſt where your ſhoe wringeth you: neither néede you any Counſaylour to bid you cut where it doth wringe you: But whereas you know it lawfull, if you ſhal thinke it alſo expedient, that of a widow you become a wife, then ought you to take good aduiſement, how you do beſtow your ſelf, leaſt you both marry and marre your ſelf in one daye, and of an happie widow, become an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie wife. I néede not ſéeke farre to ſhew you the daungers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſutche leapte into, that in this matter raſhly leaped before they wiſely looked: becauſe the common experience in others, may leade you through the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion hereof, euen as ſtreight as a line. And therefore I will not counſell you as nedeleſſe to aduiſement, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende you that you haue hitherto ſtande ſo ſtaied with ſutche aduiſed deliberacion.</p>
                  <p>Onely this pointe I finde in you, which néedeth a knot, to conſider how you might do moſt aduiſedly, what match were moſte méete for you to be made, that repentance fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not, to what marke you ought to direct your counſel, aduiſement, and deliberation, that the ſucceſſe might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15694:27"/>your hope, that is, that it might turne to continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comforte, and to the glorie of God.</p>
                  <p>This verely I wot well, is a caſe of ſutche importance to conſider, and hath ſo many harde knottes to worke on, that it were more fit for gray heares, ſage wittes, and déepe Diuines, to take in hande, then for my ſimplicitie to aduenture. I am (in this caſe) of like opinion with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius</hi> the Emperour of Rome, who ſayd: <hi>If all the wiſe men in the worlde were molten together in a Fornace, they coulde not giue one good counſell to make a Mariage.</hi> What counſell then may you looke to haue at my handes: if a wiſe man, if many wiſe men, if all the wiſe, bee not wiſe inoughe in any pointe well to aduertiſe you in this behalfe? Wherefore I beſéeke you, impute not that for preſumption vnto mee, which onely good will doth force mee to aduenture, deſiryng you rather to waye the will then the witte, whiche here by mee ſhalbe ſhewen. And if I ſhall ouerſhoote my ſelfe by any pointe of foly, (as of likelyhoode I ſhall) yet let ſutche wiſedome reſte in you, that you make not that open and common, whiche bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte vs is priuate and priuie. Therefore to enter my purpoſe, becauſe that of many, yet muſt but one ioygne with one, and becauſe where one is to be choſen, it is good to ſée whiche amongſte all, if it might bee: I will bee ſo bolde, to ſet before you foure ſutche ſuiters, as may repreſent vnto you all the reſt that may happen hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to come vnto you. Conſider all by foure, trie foure, and truſte one.</p>
                  <p>There are thrée markes generally, whiche are to bée conſidered in man, whereat you maye ſhoote out your game: The inwarde minde of the man, the outewarde perſonage, and the ſtate wherein he ſtandeth of thinges apperteinyng to the worlde. By this rule I will ſeuer and ſingle out the ſortes of men, that after the diuiſion, you may with leſſe doubte make your choyce. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to beginne with the worſte: there are men that liue neither well nor welthy, beyng in a deſperate ſtate, bothe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15694:28"/>towarde God and the world, paſte hope, and paſte ſhame? But wée may ſet theſe aſide out of our number, as wee finde them, ſo let vs leaue them, for I doubte not, but as they are nought worthie, ſo you will not haue to doo with them, none of theſe I thinke will come vnto you in the name of a ſuiter.</p>
                  <p>The next man is not ſo well fauoured, nor ſo wiſe, as wealthie, not ſo courteous, as couetous, not ſo well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered, as monied, &amp; he hauyng hope through his wealthe, peraduenture will attempte you, for what caſe is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in this worlde, to ſutche as Fortune laugheth vpon. This man you may ſoone eſpie, where his treaſure is, there is his harte, euen ſutche kynde of wooynge ſhall you haue of him, as Sathan vſed to our Sauiour Chriſt, in the fourth of <hi>Mathew:</hi> If thou wilt fall downe and worſhippe me, I will geue you (ſaith hée) all theſe, you ſhalbe my Miſtreſſe of ſo many Shéepe, ſo many Oxen, and thus mutche Money ſhalbe yours as mine owne, ſo harpeth he vppon his halfepenie. But let vs ſet him aſide a while, and brynge an other in place, ſutche a one that is handſome of perſonage, a tall Gentleman, a proper man, well borne, graced with ſome courtely behauiour, well ſpoken, hauing a pretie naturall witte, adorned and graced with other ſutche qualities of the bodie, and yet peraduenture Vertue hath taken litle or no roote in him, he worſhippeth God at leyſure, and hath ſome ciuill god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in him, his religion he vſeth as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> market ſerueth, and thus doth hee recken his game: I ſée not (ſaieth hee to himſelfe) why I ſhoulde deſpayre, I ſée not but I am worthy of as good as ſhe is, I come of as good an houſe as ſhe, mine aunceſters were al gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and worſhipful: I doubt not the miſliking of my behauior, for I haue not béen ſo ill brought vp, but I know how to entertayne a gentlewoman, I ſhal ſe well inough that my demeanour be courteous and courtely, as for my perſonage and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, I force not who behold it: So to himſelf he ſaith, when to you he ſhall commende himſelf with ſome more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15694:28"/>manerly modeſty, as to ſay, he is not diſfigured, nor mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And what he cannot for ſhame ſay of himſelf, ſome other freende of his ſhall ſet out in playner termes: his fréendes indéede (peraduenture not yours) will ſo blaze his armes, as though they ſhould ſell him vnto you, as if you ſhould take him at their worde, beſettinge him with theſe and ſutche like flowers: if you reſpect the perſonage of a man, if you refuſe him, you ſhall not be ſo matched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: marke him and view him well, ſe what deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie you may finde in him: is there any parte of him out of ioynt, or out of ſquare? Marke what a ioly complexion he hath, ſée whether you may eſpie any warte or blemiſh in his viſage: conſider whether he be not a very gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in his behauiour, forget not his qualities how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable they are, his actiuitie, his mery conceites, his pretie practiſes: ſée how clenly and trimme hee is in his apparel, how ſkilful and neate he is aboute his horſe, his hawkes, and his houndes: his exerciſe alſo that hee vſeth is gentlemanlike, abrode he vſeth his bowe, within dores he can ſinge &amp; play on the Lute, &amp; as for learning, though peraduenture he hath litle or none at al, yet will they ſay he hath inough for a gentleman: and here peraduenture y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe ſaying of <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſhalbe ſcarce wiſely alleadged in the ſeuenth chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus. <hi>Be not too wiſe.</hi>
                     </hi> If he haue a good wit indéede, then ſhall there be great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes of compariſons fet: if he be but meane in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, then will they ſay, hee is no foole, no naturall: If he bee peraduenture ſomewhat ſtayned in Fame, you ſhall haue that iſſue ſtraite ſtopped with ſome playſter of excuſe: if it be not manifeſt, then will they ſaye it is falſe and forged, no man is hable to charge him ſo, the beſt are moſte ſubiect to corruption, the ſineſt clothe may bee ſooneſt ſtayned, the honeſteſt man may be ſooneſt ſlaundred: and if it bee not denied, yet it ſhalbe excuſed, as the toyes and pranckes that run in common courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge yonge men: then will it bee fayde that a man is not to be reiected, but to be borne withall in ſutche caſes:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15694:29"/>and ſo, if there appere any good gift, it ſhalbe ſet out as it were a ſonnyng to beholde: But if there bee any ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of vice, or otherwiſe any wante or defecte, that ſhall eyther be let ſlippe with ſilence, or els the broken peeces ſhalbe glewed together in ſome kinde of ſorte, that which is vnſeemely or vnſightly, ſhall haue a better coloure ſet on it with ſome gloſinge tale: the wante of witte ſhalbe ſupplied with aboundance of wealthe: euell manners with mutche money. If his life bee ſuſpected, you muſte looke in his face, for with ſome women, the pleaſing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage ſatiſfieth for it ſelfe, and alſo for vertue: And good qualities for learnyng in a Gentleman. If the quiuer bee well furniſhed, if it be well in the Stable, the Mewe and the Kenell, it dothe not mutche force what is in the Houſe, the Chambre, and the Studie. Sutch verely is the Table talke now adayes amonge Gentlemen. Sutche boltes ſhootes ſuiters, and ſuiters fréendes, and with ſutche traynes ſome women are entrapped, with ſutche winleſſes are ſome driuen into the nette of miſhap: But I truſt your eye ſight ſerueth you better, then to be dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſutch miſtes, or dazled with ſutch ſhorte ſonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinynges.</p>
                  <p>Now in the degrée of my ſuiters, the third remaineth, whom if you only iudge by the eye, that diſcerneth no farther then the face: or if you waye the worthe of your mariage with weightes of ſiluer, this man perchaunce ſhall ſoone be put out of countenance &amp; hope, he ſhal ſoone be counteruailed and wayed downe to the grounde, for he may ſinge ſaynct <hi>Peters</hi> ſonge, <hi>Siluer and golde haue I litle or none:</hi> Hee cannot number his Landes, his Leaſes, his Farmes, nor his Tenements: He hath a competente li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, but not aboundinge, or flowyng with ful ſtreame: He is no Knight, nor Alderman, but a playne Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: not highly borne, but verie well brought vp: not ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, as worſhip worthie: not of greate eſtimacion, but of ſinguler honeſtie: not ſo longe trayned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courte, as conuerſant in the ſchoole: his Landes are not ſo great,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15694:29"/>as his learning: his cheſt is not ſo ſtored with money, as his head and minde poſſeſſed &amp; furniſhed with the truſtie treaſure of trueth, and the ineſtimable wealth of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: his demaynes with others are not comparable, but his demeanour aboue others commendable: his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce is not wanton or alluringe, but yet hee hath a manly viſage, a face in which appeareth more grace then fauour: more grauitie then beauty: his tongue ſpéedinge wordes no faſter then they may ſeeme well beſtowed, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his mouth in his hart, &amp; not his hart in his mouth: hée is not ſo wel freended of men, as fauoured of GOD: his bodye is not ſo handſome of makinge, as his ſoule is well faſhioned and framed to Godward: his legge not ſo cleane, as his life without ſpot: his hand not ſo white to ſée, as his hart ſure to truſt: not highe of ſtature, yet his wit not ſhort: his body not ſo ſtraight, as his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vpright: not ſo braue in his apparrell, as graue in his behauiour: not curious and neate, but honeſt and cleanly: not ſo well faced, as wel lyued: I meane, not ſo well attyred in the outwarde man, as cloathed in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde man.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are mee thinkes the degrées of men to bée conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in our purpoſe, for I can recken no other markes whereunto Women directe their eyes and thoughtes. But there are ſome to bee found, I thinke, if wee ſecke far, in whom Vertue, Fortune, and fauour haue made a Mariage: and ſuch a one, if my prayer might bee heard, you ſhould ſoone attayne: But ſuch Startes ſhoote not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſuch Byrdes flie ſeldome abroad: yet if there happen any ſuch wherupon your conſideration ſhall ſtande, my counſell is, that you follow the example of the Phiſition, who to know the whole eſtate of a man, openeth and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him vp, and deuideth him into partes, and thereby groweth into a greater knowledge: ſo I wiſhe you to make an Anatomie of him that you haue in hande, make no confuſion of wealth, witte, body, ſoule, life, and liuing, for ſo you may ſoone deceaue your ſelfe. In one man
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15694:30"/>therfore, you may conſider thrée things, as I ſayd before: the inwarde minde, the outwarde perſon, and the ſtate wherein hee ſtandeth, of thinges appertaininge to the world: of the which thrée, you ought to chooſe but one, leaſt perhappes you miſtake your right marke, and leeſe your game: leaſt in ſtéede of a man, you finde but the ſhadow of a man. Refer your ſelfe to the patterne of thoſe perſons, which I haue rudely deſcribed vnto you: compare vnto them, and thoſe betwixt themſelues. Wherfore to enter the compariſon, if you aſke my iudgemente: the Poets to lay the foundation of a farther inuention, fained there were thrée Goddeſſes in contention for their beautie, who did moſt excell: <hi>Iuno</hi> who had the diſpoſition of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignitie: <hi>Pallas</hi> at whoſe pleaſure were all the guiftes of wifedome: and <hi>Venus</hi> the Lady of Loue. To ende this ſtrife, it pleaſed <hi>Iupiter</hi> and other Goddes, to refer the iudgement hereof to one <hi>Paris</hi> a Shapeherde, conuayinge to him a golden Apple, with this inſcription or Sentence engraned: <hi>Let it bee giuen to the fayreſt.</hi> The foreſayde Goddeſſes preſented themſelues beefore this their appoynted Iudge, and offered euery one their reward, to haue ſentence on their ſide: <hi>Iuno</hi> would make him the higheſt: <hi>Pallas</hi> the wiſeſt: and <hi>Venus</hi> a huſband of the fayreſt. <hi>Venus</hi> here preuayled, ſhe was pronounced the faireſt. <hi>Paris</hi> had his reward, that was the beautiful <hi>Helena,</hi> who (they ſay) was the cauſe of the deſtruction of the <hi>Troians.</hi> Now if your Mariage ſtoode vpon the guifte and deliuery of an Apple, I truſt you would not play <hi>Paris</hi> part, that <hi>Venus</hi> ſhould vanquiſh you. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my counſel is, that rather you cncline to <hi>Pallas</hi> for ſome reward of wit, then eyther to <hi>Iuno</hi> for her honour, or <hi>Venus</hi> for pleaſure. And beſides theſe, there is one that by right hath greater intereſt in the Apple, then any of the other, although ſhee ſtriue not ſo much for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I meane the Lady <hi>Vertue.</hi> Wherfore, if ſhe come in place, withholde not your hand from her for feare of the other, if ſhee offer not her ſelfe at the firſt, yet be not raſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15694:30"/>or haſtie, but call vnto God that hee may ſende her vnto you, and hee no doubt, as his eares are alwayes open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the prayers of the faithfull, ſhall bring her euen home to you: and ſhe, I thinke, is for your purpoſe: to her (as you ought) deliuer vp your Apple, if you intend to giue it to the faireſt, to the beſt, and to the moſt worthy. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider well my laſt purtrayed perſon, ſtandinge in the place of my thirde ſuiter, of whom although I haue not ſet ſo faire a colour, yet if he were to be ſold, I would holde as deareſt: who though hee bee not formed of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt faſhion, yet is hee made of the fineſt mettall: whom peraduenture <hi>Iuno</hi> may ieſt at, <hi>Venus</hi> haue litle to vaunt of, and <hi>Plutus</hi> whom they call the God of ritches paſſeth not on: yet if Vertue may preuayle with you, as I hope it ſhall, you ſhalbe his, and Vertue ſhalbe yours, yea, <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> alſo pleadeth on his parte. Wherfore I counſell you, as you would giue the Apple vnto Vertue, ſo giue your wedding Ringe to be worne of the vertuous. For if it be ſo, as the Philoſopher truely diſputeth, that freendſhip cannot conſiſt but betwixt the good: how ſlender a Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age will that bee, where Vertue knitteth not the knot? where honeſty is not called to counſell? and godlyneſſe is not bid to the Brydall? The Sonne of <hi>Sirache</hi> ſayth in the ſixteenth Chapter: <hi>That man is bleſſed that hath a vertuous Wife, for the number of his yeares shalbe double.</hi> I doubt not but you are ſo vertuouſly diſpoſed, that you entend to make a happy Huſbande: ſee then that hee doe as much for you, as you for him: wheras you ſhall make him happy, foreſee that hee for want of vertue, turne not the courſe of your eſtate: but wheras you ſhall double his daies, take heede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee cut not of yours by the middle. You haue I am ſure ſome good flowers growinge, take héede they be not ouergrowen and choked, with the euill wéeder that hee ſhall bring into your ground. You are (I doubt not) diſpoſed to godlyneſſe, match not with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary diſpoſition: for then ſhall you bee as the yoake of Oxen that draweth diuerſe wayes. Vice &amp; Vertue were
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15694:31"/>neuer yet fréendes, it cauſed hatred in Bretheren, as in <hi>Cayne</hi> and <hi>Abell, Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob:</hi> How can the Lambe and the Woolfe agree togeather? no more can the vngodly with the righteous: hée that toucheth Pitch, ſhalbe defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therwith. Thinke not then that the vertuous and the vicious may make a good Maryage. Can you ſet fier and water togeather, but that they ſhall ſtir and ſtriue for the maſtery, eache to conſume the other? Stande therfore, make no haſte, for feare of the worſt: It is better to loke long, then to leape lightly: rake vp the aſhes throughly, and turne them too and fro, that you be ſure there remain no ſparke of burning vice, or at the leaſt leaue as litle as you may, and ſwéepe as cleane as you can. And marke well, I wiſh, what condition <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſetteth, when he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you your lycence to marry, in the ſeuenth Chapter to the <hi>Corinthians. <hi>The wife (ſayth hee) is bound by the Law as long as her Husband lyueth, but if her Husband bee dead, ſhee is at liberty to marry in the Lorde.</hi>
                     </hi> Wey well this reſtraint of your liberty, or rather I may ſaye the ſure ſtay of your libertie, leaſt by abuſe, you turne this libertie into a bondage. For vnleſſe you haue God before your eyes, you ſhall chaunge your libertie into ſtrayte bondage: wheras you ſoke comfort, you ſhal finde a curſe: wheras you hope for eaſe and reſte, you ſhall enter into diſeaſe and trouble: aboue all therfore, haue a ſpecial and a ſtedfaſt eye vpon this rule, that you marry in the Lord. God did make the firſt Mariage that euer was made, and I doubt not but hee made the firſt that you made: and if hée make the ſecond alſo, then ſhall you be ſure neuer to repent you of your bargaine. Hée did inſtitute Mariage as a thinge moſt holy, to his glory, and to the comforte of man: Sée therefore that you in this caſe bee boyde of all fleſhly affection as neare as you may, that you prophane not that which is holy, to your owne diſcomforte, and the diſhonour of God. Chriſt our Sauiour was preſente at a Mariage in <hi>Cana,</hi> where beſides his preſence, he honored it with his firſt miracle: hee turned Water into Wyne.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15694:31"/>I pray you make your wedding place as like <hi>Cana</hi> as you can, let Chriſte bee preſent with you: I meane, to guide your ſpitit with his holy ſpirite: turne not his miracle, make not, I meane, Water of Wyne, but let that which God hath inſtituted to your comfort, bee godly handled of you to his glory. Wheras Matrimony is honourable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all men, prouide that it turne not to your ſhame and confuſion, as you ſée in ſome. I néede not here (as it were to long) particulerly to giue you preceptes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the vertues to be embraced, and the vices to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted in men. But ſhortly as our Sauiour Chriſte an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, thou knoweſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, doo this and thou ſhalt liue: So I, you know the commaundements, méete the length of their féete, by that meaſure ſhall you well perceaue, whether his ſhooe will ſerue your foote. And one thing more in this behalf I muſt ad, not of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt, but to make a double knot of a ſingle, or a treble of a double: for the ſurer, the better: the warier, the wiſer. Bée wiſe then and beware, that you put not your heade vnder the gyrdle of the vngodly, neither ſo burthen your ſelfe, as to beare the yoake with an Infidell. For then it may ſéeme that you kept not <hi>S. Pawles</hi> Rule, as to marry in the Lorde, for that is his counſell. And what Maryage may righteouſnes make w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnrighteouſneſſe? light with darkeneſſe? Chriſt with <hi>Belyall?</hi> the vnfained Children with the faithleſſe Infidell? For here beſides the danger of diſcorde, and bodily trouble therof inſuing, there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo apparant perrill that may pearce the ſoule. For ſo ſayth the Lorde to his People <hi>Iſraell,</hi> concerninge their ioyning with ſtraunge Nations of forraine fayth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the ſeuenth of <hi>Deuteronomy. <hi>Thou shalt make no couenaunt with them</hi>
                     </hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>neither shalt thou make Mariages with them, neither giue thy Daughter vnto his Sonne, nor take his Daughter vnto thy Sonne, for they will cauſe thy ſonne to turne away from mee, and to ſerue other Gods: then will the wrath of the Lorde waxe hotte againſt thee, and diſtroy thee ſodainly.</hi> You are no Iſralite, here
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15694:32"/>might be ſayd: how then? yet a Chriſtian I trow, and by faith, the Daughter of <hi>Abraham:</hi> then this muſt you rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to bee written for your learninge. There are no <hi>Hethytes,</hi> no <hi>Amorites,</hi> no <hi>Cananites</hi> to be feared: yet are there many in our daies both faithleſſe &amp; godleſſe, as the obſtinate aduerſary of the Goſpell of God, and the double dealing, falſe diſſembling Goſpeller, in whom there is no leſſe daunger of deceit, then is in the heath niſh Hethites, and curriſh Cananites: and although the perſons be not one, yet there ſeemeth to bee litle difference in the cauſe: for firſt marke the reaſon, and then apply it.</p>
                  <p>The Mariage of a Cananite was forbidden the Iſralite for feare leaſt hee ſhould bee withdrawen from the true worſhip of the true God of Iſraell. And do wee not ſee in experience, that the wicked wife, corrupteth ſuch men as wee iudge ſometime moſt vpright in life and ſtedfaſt in profeſſion of the truth? and how much more daunger is there leaſte the vnbeleeuinge and wicked man, alter the good nature of the honeſt woman, into his owne peruerſe nature, ſéeing that to him ſhe is ſubiect, as the body to the head? you muſt of neceſſitie bee one in fleſhe with him whom you ſhall chooſe: Foreſée therfore by wiſedome, that his relygion bee chriſtian and godly with yours: ſee that you change not your manners with your name, but chooſe you ſuch a Make, as feareth God, imbraceth and loueth his holy word, and ſetteth his whole delight in his Lawes and teſtimonies. Preſume not of your ſelfe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: you are not wiſer then <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet as it appeareth in the nynth Chapter of the firſt Booke of <hi>Kinges: <hi>His wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was ſo bewitched by the meanes of thoſe forraine wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with whom hee matched in Mariage, that hee became a fond Idolater, and ſo fell into the handes of God.</hi>
                     </hi> Of this example, I truſt you will take ſufficient warning, ſo that herein I neede not to make many wordes: vnleſſe you obiect vnto mée, or ſome other vnto you, the place of <hi>Sainct Pawle</hi> in the ſeauenth Chapter to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where hee ſayth: <hi>The vnbeleeuing Huſband is ſanctified by the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15694:32"/>Wife, and the vnbeleeuing Wife, is ſanctified by the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> If wee marke the purpoſe of <hi>Sainct Pawle,</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſhall not be hard: the Verſe nexte afore, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne his purpoſe, which is, that the beleeuinge Woman already marryed to the vnbeleeuinge man, ſhould not vſe the infidelity of her Huſbande, as an occaſion to departe from him, the wordes are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Woman which hath an Husbande that beleeueth not, if hee bee content to dwell with her, let her not forſake him:</hi> and then hee ioyneth the former ſentence, as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to confirme this other ſentence, ſo that that place ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to this end &amp; purpoſe, that if you and your huſbande were firſt both of you vnbeleeuers, afterward it pleaſed God to call you to the knowledge of his truth, your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band continuing in his infidelitie, or if now being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, you ſhould aduenture to marry with an vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, you ought not being married together, to ſeke a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, becauſe there is hope of ſanctification. For as you ſhould do yl to yoake your ſelfe with an vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo ſhould you do worſe to ſhake him off, being ioyned vnto you by Maryage, without ſome iuſter cauſe, becauſe there is hope of ſanctification. And although it bee not a ſufficiente cauſe to breake the knot, that by Maryage is knit, yet it is a iuſt and neceſſary cauſe, wherfore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne Mariage. For the Maryage of an vngodly perſon I graunt is a mariage, and not lightly to be diſſolued: but yet an vngodly Maryage, and that which lacketh ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as may eaſely be gathered of the wordes of <hi>Sainct Pawle,</hi> beefore alleadged. Wherfore as I would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle you to continue, for the hope of ſanctification, if your head were faſt in the yoake, that you might winne your huſband: ſo now ſtanding frée, tempt not God I ſay, preſume not, matche not with any that you know to bee out of the houſehold of fayth, for feare of corruption, leaſt you leeſe your ſelfe, before you win an other.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I ſpoken hytherto for my third wooer, who pleadeth honeſtie, vertue, and godlyneſſe, who I doubt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15694:33"/>not ſhall ſpéede, becauſe that God is on his ſide. And here if you demaund of mée, whether I would haue you ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, as only to regarde the honeſtie and vertue, without any further reſpect. Truely, although (peraduenture) I ſhall ſéeme to ſpiritual in this point, yet if you had your eies fully fixed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that marke, without wanering other wayes, no doubt but God would proſper you the better, in aſmuch as hée ſhall therby haue tryal, that you depend wholy vpon him and his prouideuce, and then ſhal you be left in danger of ſnares. And of this, that it ought to bee ſo, we may take an example and warning of the manner that God vſed in the firſt Mariage making, in the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Geneſis: <hi>For while he was prouiding for</hi> Adam, <hi>the Woman that should be his wyfe and his comfort, he cauſed an heauy fleepe to fall vpon the Man, and while hee was a ſleepe, he toke out that Ryb wherof he framed the Woman.</hi>
                     </hi> So verely I would thinke that God did moſt worke with you, if you laide <hi>Adam</hi> a fléepe, I meane, if you remooued all carnal affections, and worldly reſpectes which proceed as earthly from <hi>Adam,</hi> while that this bargaine were a dryuing. This I know is far wide from worldly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but this way you ſhall goe neareſt, to make a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Paradice, and ſo ſhal you ſéeme moſt to marry in the Lord. And if you may not abide ſo ſtraight binding, yet ſwarue as litle as you may: If this be not your whole building, yet at the leaſt, let it be your chéefe foundation: if this be your ground, haue no doubt but there wil grow and follow other good flowers ſufficiently. So then I thinke you ſhall geather a good ſomme, if you caſte your accountes in this wiſe: If Vertue come alone, ſhe is not to be refuſed: if ſhee come with the company of ſutch as the world eſtemeth, not as a Seruant, but as a Miſtreſſe, which is hard and ſeldome, ſhe is alſo to be imbraced. But if you ſtand on this point, you are in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to ſlide: for Vertue clothed, is not ſo ſure to truſt, as if it be naked and bare. Then a litle vertue excéeding in one, may not be ſupplied with great ſtore of goods, and haboundance of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15694:33"/>ritches in another: for we muſt in our dooings firſt ſéeks the kingdome of Heauen, as for other things, after them ſeeke the Gentiles: If they bee ſought with care, euen when we thinke vs neareſt, we are oftentimes fartheſt off, and ſhoote to ſhort: If we attaine the thing deſired, yet we lacke the fruition, as when we wanted the thing: If wee enioy it, yet the ſpace is ſhorte: but if they come as vnbidden gueſtes, then are they moſt welcome: yea if we ſeeke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, the promiſe is, they ſhalbe caſt vnto vs: and if they be caſt, then come they in their kinde. Now then to ſpeake ſomewhat of other reſpectes ſeuerally, you may remember, the ſuiter whom I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto you, I did ſo qualifie, that as I would not haue him godleſſe, ſo I wiſh him not to be witleſſe, for that I recken a moſt honeſt reſpecte, ſo that you diſcerne the true wiſedome from the falſe, ſo that the ſimplicitie of the Dooue, do not ioyne with the wilines of the Serpent: neither ſhal this hinder my honeſt and godly Wooer in his ſuit, but rather further him. For as fooles are fortunate, ſo the vertuous commonly haue leſſe want of wiſedome: the feare of the Lorde is wiſedome. Chriſt is the wiſedome of God the Father: therfore if you make account of true wiſedome, in this behalf you ſhalbe beſt ſped in the true godly chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. I néede not make compariſon betwéene the godly and the wiſe, ſo that you vſe your wiſedome, to iudge and diſcerne aright of wiſedome, for the right wiſedome, the godly righteous hath obtained. Only if the compariſon ſtand betwixte the wiſe, and the wealthy or hanſome, let <hi>Salomon</hi> bee your Counſailour therin, who ſayth in the eyghth Chapter of his Prouerbes. <hi>VViſedome is better then precious Stones, and all pleaſures are not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto her:</hi> and in the ſixteenth Chapter. <hi>It is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to get wiſedome then Golde, and to get vnderſtandinge, is more to be deſired then Siluer.</hi> And in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeauenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> hée ſaith: <hi>The excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of wiſedome, giueth life to the poſſeſſers thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if the righteous and the ritch ſtand in compariſon,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15694:34"/>yet I truſt my poore ſpirited ſuiter ſhall not be out faced, you ſitting as Iudge, &amp; ſuch I truſt ſhalbe your ſentence, as was the wiſe <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> anſwere: For when it was demaunded of him, whether a man ſhould beſtowe his Daughter vpon a good poore man, or vpon a ritch man not ſo honeſt? his anſwere was, I had rather like the man that lacketh money, then money that wanteth a man. So litle thought he that ritches and ſubſtance did make a matter of Mariage, that it ſeemed to him, ſhe did not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for any regard of the man, that had ſuch reſpect of rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: and that ſhée that married not an honeſt man, did ſcarſe marrie a man. Some in déede haue their fancy ſo led, as though money made men: but let this bee your Poeſie rather when you make your Mariage: <hi>Manners makes Men.</hi> Conſider the ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the .xxxvij. Pſalm. <hi>A ſmal thing that the iuſt man hath is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great ritches of the vngodly wicked &amp; mighty.</hi> I wiſh you wealth &amp; ritches, for I know they are the good giftes of God: but I feare leaſt Vertue wilbe ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, where ſuch floods breake out. Hée that wil tarry for the company of a ritch man to goe to Heauen, it will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be long ere hée come there, for his way is as ſtraight as the eie of a Néedell, and hée himſelfe as huge as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell. <hi>Salomon</hi> in the twentie &amp; twentie one Chapters of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> maketh a maruell of the ritch vpright man. Therfore I wiſhe you, haue not this minde with you, as to ſeeke a ritche Mariage, for then you miſſe of the right marke of Mariage ordained for your comfort, there lyeth not the way leading to reſt and quietneſſe. For they that wilbe ritch, fal into ſnares and temptations, &amp; into many fooliſh &amp; noyſome luſtes, which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction. Vſe oftentimes rather to repeate this ſentence with your ſelf: <hi>The deſire of money, is the roote of all euill.</hi> Take héede that that roote ouergrow not other good flowers: but harken to the ſentence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our Sauiour pronounceth, in the ſixt Chapter of <hi>Sainct Lukes</hi> Goſpel. <hi>VVoe bee vnto you that are ritche, for you haue receaued
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15694:34"/>your conſolation.</hi> Theſe are the boundes that <hi>S. Pawle</hi> appointeth vs: <hi>If we haue</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>foode and rayment, let vs therwith be content.</hi> And truely herein conſiſteth not true ritches, to poſſeſſe this earthly treaſure, the meat of Mothes, and the bayte of Théeues. But ſuch as my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended ſuiter poſſeſſeth, if you may be partaker thereof, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may you ſay: my lot is fallen to me on a faire ground, and that you haue got a goodly poſſeſſion. Godlineſſe (ſaith the Apoſtle) is great gaine, if a man be content with that hée hath: euen that is it which my ſuiter bringeth, godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with contentacion. Wherfore then ſhould you deſire the mariage of the ritch? you ſée it bringeth no reſt: you ſée godlines is the true ritches: and God of his goodneſſe hauing already bleſſed you with ſufficient ſtore &amp; greate haboundance, I doubt not but you haue ſo good a minde with you, that you are rather vertuouſly deſirous, wiſely to imploy and beſtow your goods and ritches, then gréedily couetous, to hoard them vp, and laye heape vpon heape, with an inſatiable deſire to increaſe them. Doo you ſeke to eſtabliſh to you and yours an inheritance? harken then what the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the .xxxvij. Pſalme. <hi>The euill dooers</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>ſhalbe cut off, but they that wait vpon the Lord, they shall inherit the Lande.</hi> Againe: <hi>The meeke men</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>shall inherite and poſſeſſe the earth.</hi> And againe: <hi>The Lord knoweth the dayes of vpright men, and their inheritance shalbe perpetuall.</hi> Doo you ſéeke a continuance and perpetuitie in things? <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſayth: <hi>Like as when the Sunne ryſeth with heate, the Graſſe withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, his flowerfalleth away, and the beauty of the faſhion of it perisheth, euen ſo shall the ritche man fade away in all his wayes: but the iuſte they flourish like the Palme tree, they are like the Bay tree, euen greene and fresh like themſelues: the roote of the righteous ſhall not be mooued.</hi> Doo you deſire to haue ſuch a heade as may beſt defende you from iniuries and oppreſſions? who is of more might then the righteous &amp; godly? <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth in the .xxxiiij. Pſalme. <hi>The Angell of the Lorde pitecheth his Tente round about
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15694:35"/>them that feare him, and deliuereth them in all their necesſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And againe: <hi>The cares of the Lord are open vnto their prayers, and hee will heare their cry, yea, hee keepeth their bones that none of them be broken, he numbreth the haires of their heades that none of them be loſt.</hi> Doo you feare perrill or penury? of the godly righteous thus ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the .xxxvij. Pſalme. <hi>They shall be confounded in the perrilous time, and in the dayes of famine they shal haue ynough.</hi> You will peraduenture ſay, for my ſelfe I can holde mée well ynough contente, but my Childrens caſe mooueth mée.</p>
                  <p>Harken then what <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of his experience in the xxxvij Pſalme. <hi>I haue been younge</hi> (ſaith hée) <hi>and am now old, yet ſaw I neuer the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begginge their bread.</hi> Doubtleſſe God ſhall prouide for you and yours ſufficiently and haboundantly, if you caſts away all ſuch worldly reſpectes, and much more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. Now I thinke theſe ſhall ſuffiſe to vnderſet and ſtaye you vp that you fall not on this ſide.</p>
                  <p>The nexte care concerneth my fourth Suiter, that hes take you not with the bayt of beauty, wherby many wiſe Women and Men haue bin deceaued, and with a ſhorte pleaſure haue purchaſed long and deſperate repentance.</p>
                  <p>This cauſed <hi>Salomon</hi> to commit folly, as appeareth in the ſeconde Chapter of the firſt Booke of <hi>Kinges.</hi> This cooled the mighty <hi>Sampſons</hi> courage, as is manifeſted by the ſixtéenth Chapter of the Booke of <hi>Iudges.</hi> Did not the beauty of <hi>Bethſaba</hi> ſo rauiſhe the eyes of holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he committed with her moſt habominable Adultery, and made himſelfe gyltie of bloodſhed? ſo it is written in the ſecond Chapter of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Samuell. Hee ſaw a Woman washinge her ſelfe, and the Woman was very beautifull to looke vpon. &amp;c.</hi> You might abuſe theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to folly, as to ſaye: Theſe men were notable, for ſtrength, for wiſedome, for godlineſſe: maruell not then (might you ſay) though I be ouercome in that caſe. Not ſo, good Coſin, but this conſider in theſe examples, that if
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15694:35"/>ſuch of ſo excellent graces, haue béen led away with theſe traynes: you haue hereby a faire warninge, to beware, and to be very circumſpecte, in ſo ſubtill a pointe, and ſo daungerous a caſe: if you giue place to ſuch fancies that they ouercome reaſon, you may ſoone ſlip into thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences that you ſee in the examples of others, you may pluck the houſe on your owne head, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did. As you chooſe your marke, ſo goeth your game: as you make your foundacion, ſo will your buildinge bée: if the one be ſtedfaſt, the other will not lightly ſhake: but if the one be not ſurely grounded, a litle blaſt marreth mutch worke. Surely the hanſome perſon of man is not of long continuance: beſides that it is ſubiecte to corruption by inuulnerable meanes. Wherfore, if your Mariage hang vpon that knot, a litle force will breake it, a litle labour will vndo it, and of it ſelfe it wil decay and weare away. If this fancie bee the leader of your loue, you folow a blinde guide, you may ſoone ſlide, and wander out of the right waye. Many an vnſauery woode, beareth a faire bloſſome: and ſo vnder a faire face, their lyeth hidden many a foule fault, and with a ſound looke, oftentimes is couered the holow harte, full of all hatred, whereof you may reade a louely example of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> in the fourſéenth Chapter of the ſeconde Booke of <hi>Samuell.</hi> I haue read an Hiſtory of one <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Rome,</hi> matched with a Wife called <hi>Papiria,</hi> both for byrth and beauty (to iudge) worthy ſuch a Huſbande: howbeit hes deuorced her, and when her fréendes infreated for her, demaunding of him what ſhould be the cauſe that moued him ſo to doo, for they ſaw none, ſéeinge that ſhée was to beholde, mannerly and m<hi rend="sup">o</hi>odeſt, faire and fruitfull. Then hée for anſwere, thruſteth out his foote, and ſaith: behold, ſée my ſhoe, is it not faire? is it not new? yet none of you wotteth where it doth wringe mée. Belike there was ſome ſecret fault in that Woman not to bee borne with, which was ſo lothſome vnto the Huſband, as her beautie could be pleaſaunt, Bée aduiſed therfore, leaſt you finde
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15694:36"/>that your handſome huſband haue that, which this man found in his faire Wife. If you will not that your ſhoe wringe you, meaſure him before you buy, and iudge not of him by the colour: but meaſure him rather within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without, leaſt you wring for it afterwarde. The goodly perſonage without wiſedome and vertue, what is it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a paynted man? <hi>Plato</hi> the wiſe Philoſopher, thus ſayd to <hi>Alcibiades: <hi>Hee that at any time hath loued</hi> Alcibiades <hi>body, hath not loued</hi> Alcibiades <hi>himſelfe: but he that loueth thee, loueth thy minde and ſoule.</hi>
                     </hi> And the wiſe <hi>Tully</hi> ſayth: <hi>Man is as his minde is, and not that forme and figure which may be pointed at with the finger.</hi> For man conſiſteth of two partes: the one is the minde endued with reaſon, and beareth the Image of God: the other is the body, which wee haue common with brute Beaſtes. <hi>Dauid</hi> compareth that man that lacketh vnderſtandinge, vnto Horſe and Mule: and mée thinkes, I may wel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſuch luſty lads, whoſe commendacion is only in their perſonage, and lacketh learninge wit and honeſty, vnto <hi>Platoes man,</hi> as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſcoffingly termed. For when that <hi>Plato</hi> in his Schoole had defined a man in this wiſe, to be a lyuing and two footed creature, made vpright and without any feathers: <hi>Diogenes</hi> thinkinge that hee had not well defined or expreſſed the nature of man, becauſe hee ſuppreſſed that which was moſt propper to man, and did concerne the minde and guift of reaſon: hee plucked a Capon bare of all his feathers, and turned him into the Schoole, ſaying: beholde <hi>Platoes</hi> man.</p>
                  <p>Thus is a man if you conſider not his minde, a foole: What is he but an vnfeathered fowle. A man without manners, what is hée better then a Capon without fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? wherfore if you meete any ſutche in your diſhe, eſteeme him as you liſt, I haue tolde you the price. Truſt not to ſoone thoſe faire faces, which come like Capons vpon Soppes and Suger. That braue apparrell, what is it elſe but Peacockes feathers? The good complexion, the ſtrength of the body, the white hande, the cleane leg,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15694:36"/>what are they all, but fadinge flatteringe flowers? what but baytes to deceaue the fooliſh fiſhe? All theſe doo ſerue but to pleaſe the eye, &amp; to ſatiſfie the fantacy of the fleſh. Conſider that which is written in the ſirte Chapter of <hi>Geneſis. <hi>The Sonnes of God ſaw the Daughters of men that they were fayre, and they toke them Wiues of all that they Iyked. Therfore the Lord ſayd: my ſpirit shall not alwaies ſtriue with man. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi> Beholde that fleſhly fancy euen of Mariage it ſelfe, becauſe therby they abuſed and polluted the holy ordenaunce of God, is expreſſed there, as one of the cauſes, that prouoked God, ſo to powre out the rayne of his wrath, and to deſtroy all fleſhe from the face of the earth. Wherfore in this point I ende with the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Sainct Iohn,</hi> in the ſeconde Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle. <hi>Loue not the worlde, neither the things that are in the world: if any man loue the world, the loue of the Father is not in him: for al that is in the world, as the luſt of the flesh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pryde of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world: and the world paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof: but hee that fulfilleth the will of God, abideth for euer.</hi> By theſe you may conſider the true and ſure way you haue to walke: you haue the by wayes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may cauſe you to wander, in ſome part ſtopped vp: you may ſée, if it pleaſe yon, the good, and the bad, although ſet forth but in a rude glaſſe. Singe not now <hi>Medeas</hi> ſonge, who ſayd: <hi>I ſee and allow the better, but yet I follow the worſe.</hi> Giue not <hi>Venus</hi> your Apple, but giue the vertuous your wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge Ringe. And then ſée how you haue headed your Arrow: ſée the bleſſed ſtate you ſtande in: hee is yours, for better, for worſer, forritcher, for poorer, in ſickeneſſe &amp; in health: hée ſhalbe to you an Huſbande, to your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren a Father, to your fréendes a fauourer, to your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies a terror: hee ſhall willingly beare parte of all your blowes and burdens: hee ſhall double your proſperitie: hee ſhal mourne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you wéepe: hée ſhal laugh when you are glad: his loue is ſure ſealed, euen ioyned by God him ſlfe. Hée is not like the ritche, of whom the Sonne of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15694:37"/>Sirache ſayth in the thirtéenth Chapter. <hi>If thou bee for his profit, hee vſeth thee, but if thou haue nothing, hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh thee.</hi> Hée is not like the light louer of Beauty, of whom the wiſe <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith: <hi>Hee that loueth thee for thy fauour, when that decayeth hee will giue thee ouer.</hi> But hee ſhall bee one wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you both body and ſoule, hee ſhal walke forth with you all your Pilgrimage here on earth, &amp; ſhall leade you the way to eternall reſt.) Hee ſhal bée bleſſed in all his affaires, for ſo ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> in the hundred &amp; four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth Pſalme: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, and delighteth in his commaundementes, the generation of him shalbe bleſſed, ritches and treaſures shalbe in his houſe, and his righteouſneſſe shal indure.</hi> And in the hundred &amp; twentie eyght Pſalme hée ſayth: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, and walketh in his wayes: when hee eateth the laboures of his handes hee shalbe bleſſed, and it ſhalbe wel with him: his Wife shalbe as the flourishinge Vyne on the ſides of his houſe: euen your Husbandes Wife shal bee ſuch a one, if your Huſbande bee ſuch a one:</hi> This <hi>Dauid</hi> promiſeth, and in the ſpirit of God propheſieth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it againe, ſaying: <hi>Loe, ſurely thus shal the man be bleſſed that walketh in the wayes of the Lord, and thus shall the Woman bee bleſſed that marryeth the man that feareth the Lorde.</hi> You wil ſay, peraduenture, I would thinke my ſelfe well beſtowed vpon ſuch a man: but the crafte is in the catching, the doubt is in the obtayninge. But goe you forwarde in your race of Vertue, and then you ſhall not goe far before you meete with a méete matche. It is an olde ſayinge: <hi>The like loueth the like.</hi> The Sonne of <hi>Sirache</hi> ſayth in the thirtéenth Chapter. <hi>All flesh wil reſort to their like, and euery man wil kepe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with ſuch as hee is himſelfe. A vertuous Woman</hi> (ſaith hée in the ſixtéenth Chapter) <hi>is a good portion, and a gyfte to be giuen to ſome iuſt <hi>ioſeph,</hi> or ſome true <hi>Tobyas.</hi>
                     </hi> You know that euery good gifte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from God, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and firſt founder therof: and ſurely in this caſe God appeareth more euidente to ſtrike the ſtroke, &amp; to worke
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15694:37"/>as it were immediatly within, with his owne hande: So ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi> in the nynetéenth Chapter of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes: <hi>Houſe and ritches are the inheritance of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but a prudent Wife is the ſpeciall guiſee of the Lorde.</hi> Wherfore, although there bee good tokens and markes wherby to make your choice, as by the fruite to iudge the Trée: for ſo ſaith the Booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> in the .xxvij. Chapter: <hi>The worde declareth the harte, the talke is the tryall of men:</hi> Yet becauſe theſe are rather probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures, then ſure demonſtracions, for Fame oftentimes lyeth: therefore when you haue caſte the whole and the ſomme, yet God is all in all this matter, and the onely maker of good Mariages. Bee free then from worldly buſineſſe, he cleare from carnall affections, caſt your hope vpon God, depend vpon his prouidence, commit the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wholy to his handes, reſorte and flye to him with oft and earneſt prayer: for that when all other wayes bee tryed, is the plaineſt to ſeeke, the ſureſt to truſt, and the readieſt to finde, for ſuch as ſeeke good Wiues, and good Huſbandes. You haue a good example in the .xxiiij. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> how <hi>Abraham</hi> proceeded in the Mariage of his Sonne <hi>Iſaac:</hi> You haue there the praier that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of <hi>Abraham</hi> made, to whom the charge therof was committed, how hée entringe his iourney deſired God to proſper him, and to ſhew mercy vnto his Maiſter <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and that God according to his faithfull prayer, gaue him a token, wherby hée choſe the vertuous Virgin <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca.</hi> For her Parentes, when they perceaued that God wrought with man, could not deny their good will vnto <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but anſwered: <hi>This thing is proceeded of the Lorde, we cannot therfore ſay vnto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee eyther euill or good.</hi> You haue alſo there the exerciſe of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> how he was occupied in the meane time, while <hi>Rebecca</hi> was taken out of his Ryb: hée wente out to praye in the Féelde towardes the euening, and <hi>Rebecca</hi> firſt found him ſo occupied. This is all (my good Coſin) that I haue now to be ſayd. Giue your ſelfe ouer wholy vnto God to bee your guide. Let
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15694:38"/>your eyes be ſo earneſtly bente vpon him, as they were wont to be vpon your Miſtreſte, whom you haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſerued: Then ſhall God no doubt giue you as a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the rightuous, hée ſhall ſo ioyne you, that man may not ſeperate you: Chriſt ſhal bee preſent with you, as at the Mariage of <hi>Cana:</hi> hee ſhall conduct you with his holy ſpirit: he ſhall turne your Water into Wine: hee ſhall make the ſower ſweete, and proſper all your affaires. In the meane time, while God worketh, bee not you ydle, but practiſe your ſelfe in <hi>Iſaackes</hi> exerciſe, and God ſhall ſende you an Huſbande of his kinde, euen a faithfull Sonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> a choſen Childe of God. Yea, God ſhal ſende his Aungell to lead that man vnto your houſe, euen as hee brought <hi>Tobyas</hi> vnto <hi>Sara,</hi> at the houſe of her Father <hi>Raguell.</hi> And as my poore prayer may helpe, I will become your faythfull Orator, I will beſeeke the Lorde God to guide you with his holy ſpirite, to prouide you an Huſband for your comfort, and to graunt you long to liue and loue togeather, to your deſired hartes eaſe, and vnſpeakeable quiet. And ſo I leaue to trouble you, and betake you to God, who I am ſure will neuer forget you, if you repoſe your whole confidence in him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours to commaund during lyfe, I. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This faythfull pledge of true intente, With truſtie harte is truely mente.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15694:38"/>
                  <p>THE GLASSE of godly Loue.</p>
                  <p>Wherin all maried couples may learne their duties, each toward o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, according to the holy Scriptures: Verye neceſſary for all maryed men and women, that feare the Lorde, &amp; loue his lawes, to haue it in their Bedchambers, daily to looke in: whereby they may know, and do their duties each vnto others, and leade a godly, quiet, and louing life togeathers, to the glory of God, and the good example of their Chriſtian Bretheren.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Iames. 1.</bibl> See that ye be not only hearers of the worde, but alſo doers, leaſt that therby yee deceaue your ſelues.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Coloſſians. 3.</bibl> Aboue all thinges put on Loue, which is the band of perfection.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:15694:39"/>
                  <head>To all Chriſtian men and <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that are maryed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch, as the Diuel is moſt</hi> ready to make ſtrife where there ought to bee moſt loue: and hath with heddy wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, concupiſcence, and ignorance, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blinded the hartes of thoſe which liue vnder the yoke of Matrimony (that as I may iudge by their fruites) there be very few that leade their lyues therein, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the lawes of Chriſte. Therfore (my deare &amp; welbeloued Chriſtians, which profeſſe the Goſpell) to the intent that you ſhould liue therin, according to your profeſſion and knowledge: I haue here breefely and plaincly ſet forth what it is, and how you ought to leade your lyues therin, accordinge to the Rules of the holy Scriptures, ſo that your pure and godly lyfe may bee a good example, and alſo make ſuch aſhamed as would ſclaunder the holy Goſpell, and profeſſours of the ſame: yea, and that their wonted worde (which is, marke theſe new men by their lyuinge) may ſound to Gods glory, to the honour of his moſt holy worde, and praiſe of al them in Chriſt, which do profeſſe the ſame. Farewell in the Lorde.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:15694:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall firſt vnderſtande,</hi> that Wedlocke is an hie and bleſſed order or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God in Paradiſe, which hath euer bin had in great honor and reuerence, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n, one man and one woman are coupled and knit togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one fleſhe and body, in the feare and loue of God, by the frée, louing, hartie, and good conſent of them both, to the intente that they two may dwel togeather, as one fleſh and bodye, of one will and minde, in all godlyneſſe, moſt louingly to helpe and comfort one another, to bring forth children, and to inſtruct them in the lawes of God. Alſo to auoyde Fornication and all vncleaneneſſe, and ſo in all honeſty, vertue, and godlyneſſe, to ſpend their liues in the equall partakinge of all ſuch thinges as God ſhall ſend them, with thankes gyuinge.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe that the Wife is in ſubiection to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, I will begin with her, &amp; ſhortly declare what dutie and obedience ſhée oweth vnto him, by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the Scriptures.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. The duetie of the Wife, to her Husband.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SAynct Pawle</hi> ſayth: <hi>Yee Wiues, ſubmit your ſelues to your owne Husbandes, as to Lorde: for the Husband is the Wiues head, as Chriſt is the head of the Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Therfore as the Congregation is in ſubiection vnto Chriſte, likewiſe let Wiues be in ſubiection to their Husbandes in al thinges.</hi> So that the wife muſt bee obediente vnto her huſband, as vnto Chriſt himſelfe, whereout it foloweth, that the ſaide obedience extendeth not vnto any wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or euill, but vnto that which is good, honeſt, and cumly. In aſmuch as God delighteth onely in goodnes, &amp; forbiddeth the euill euery where: it foloweth alſo, that the diſobedience that a wife ſhoweth to hir Huſband, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth God no leſſe, then when he is diſobeyed himſelf. For the wife ought to obey hir huſband in all pointes, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15694:40"/>the Congregation to Chriſte, which loueth Chriſt onely: and aboue all thinges, ſhee is glad and willinge to ſuffer for Chriſtes ſake, ſhee doth all for the loue of him, Chriſte only is her romfort, ioy, and all togeathers, vpon Chriſte is hir thought daye and night, ſhée longeth onely after Chriſt, for Chriſtes ſake (if it may ſerue to his glory) ſhée is hartely well contented to die, yee ſhee giueth ouer her ſelfe wholly therto, for Chriſtes loue, knowing aſſuredly that hir ſoule, hir honour, body, lyfe, and all that ſhe hath is Chriſtes owne. Thus alſo muſt euery honeſt Wife ſubmit hir ſelf, to pleaſe hir Huſband with all hir power, and giue hir ſelfe fréely, and willingly, to loue him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him, and neuer to forſake him till the houre of death.</p>
                     <p>And farther (ſayth <hi>S. Peter:</hi>) <hi>Let the Wiues be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecton to their Husbandes, that euen they which beleeue not the worde, may without the worde be wonne by the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Wiues, while they beholde your pure conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation coupled with feare, whoſe apparrell shall not bee out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with brodred haire, and hanging on of Golde, either in putting on of gorgious apparrell, but let the hid man of the harte bee vncorrupt, with a meeke and quiet ſpirit, which ſpirit is before God much ſet by, for after this manner in the olde time did the holy Women which truſted in God tire themſelues, and were obedient to their Husbandes, euen as <hi>sara</hi> obeyed <hi>Abraham:</hi> and called him hir Lorde, whoſe Daughters ye are as long as ye do well.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaking vnto <hi>Tytus</hi> (ſayth hée:) <hi>Let the elder Women be in ſuch apparrell as becommeth holineſle, not beeing falſe accuſers, not giuen to much Wine, but that they teache honeſt thinges, to make the young Women ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber minded, to loue their Husbandes, to loue their Children, to be diſcrete, chaſte, huſwifely, good, obedient vnto their Husbandes, that the worde of God be not euill ſpoken of.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>VVhat a Wife ought to bee.</head>
                     <p>HEre may you learne, that a Wife ought to be diſcret, chaſte, huſwifely, ſhamefaſt, good, méeke, pacient, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15694:40"/>ſober, not light in countenance, nor gariſhe in apparrell, with dyed or curled haire, painted nor paſted, but with a cumly grauitie and a ſad behauiour of a conſtant minde, true tongued, and of few wordes, with ſuch obedience in all godlyneſſe to her Huſbande and head, as it beſeemes a Chriſtian to haue vnto Chriſt, and to the intente that the Huſband in like caſe may learne his duetie, let him har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken what <hi>Sainct Pawle</hi> ſayth: and take heede that hee turne not his authoritie to tyranny.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The dutie of the Husband to his Wyfe.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HVſbandes loue your Wiues</hi> (ſayth hée) <hi>as Chriſt loued the Congregation, and gaue him ſelfe to ſanctifie it.</hi> Now muſt you vnderſtande, that the Huſbande is the Wiues head, as Chriſte is the head of the congregation: and Chriſt ſhoweth to the congregation the ſame thinge, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head ſhoweth to the bodye: for like as the head ſeeth and heaveth for the whole body, ſtudieth and deuiſeth for to preſerue it in ſtrength and life: euen ſo doth Chriſte defend, teach, and preſerue his congregation. For hee is the eye, hart, wiſedome, and guide therof: ſo ought Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands (then) to loue their wines, &amp; be their heads in like manner to ſhow them like kindeneſſe, and after the ſame faſhion to guide them and rule them with diſcretion, for their preſeruacion, &amp; not with force or wilfulneſſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them. And <hi>S. Pawle</hi> ſaith farther: <hi>So ought men to loue their wiues, as their owne bodies: he that loueth his wife loueth himſelf. For no man hath at any time hated his owne flesh, but doth nourish and cherish it, euen as the Lorde doth the Congregation.</hi> Therfore, ought euery man moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to loue his wife equally w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> himſelfe in al pointes: for this is the meaſure of mutuall loue Matrimoniall, that either partie haue nothing ſo deare that they can not be contented to beſtow one vpon another, ye, and if neede ſhould be, they ſhould alſo not ſpare their owne liues one for another, no more then chriſt did for his congregation.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15694:41"/>And like as when we repent and beléeue in the promiſe of God in Chriſt (though we were neuer ſo poore ſinners) are as ritch as Chriſt, &amp; al merites ours: ſo is a Woman (though ſhe were neuer ſo poore afore ſhe was maried) as ritch as hir huſband, for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath is hirs, ye his owne bodye, and hath power ouer it, as ſaith <hi>Sainct Pawle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if it ſo chaunce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you finde not your wife ſo perfect in al pointes, as you would or as your ſelfe, yet muſt you not diſpiſe hir, nor bee bitteer nor cruell vnto hir for hir faultes, but gently and louingly, ſeeke to amend and win hir. For like as Chriſte thought no ſcorne of his church, diſpiſed hir not, neither forſooke hir for hir vncleanenes and ſinnes: ſo ſhould no chriſtian man ſpurne at his wife nor ſet light by hir, becauſe that ſometime ſhe falleth, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth, or goeth not right, but euen as Chriſt nouriſheth and teacheth his church, ſo ought euery honeſt huſbande (alſo) louingly and gently to informe &amp; inſtruct his wife.</p>
                     <p>For in many things (ſaith <hi>S. Peter</hi>) God hath made the men ſtronger then the women, not to rage vpon them &amp; to be tirantes vnto them, but to helpe them &amp; beare their weakeneſſe. Bee curteous therfore (ſaith hée) and win them to Chriſt, and ouercome them with kindeneſſe, that of loue they may obey the ordinance that God made bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene man and Wife.</p>
                     <p>Oh how aſhamed be thoſe men to loke vpon this texte, which with violence in their furye will intreate their wiues: no beaſt ſo beaſtly, for in the moſt cruelſt way is not mete, as when the wife is ſad and diſquieted, then with ſpiteful wordes and wanton faſhions, ſo prouoking hir to anger. Where it is not the dutie of the huſband, but rather aſhamed to his owne head: likewiſe it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for a man to haue the feare of the Lorde before his eyes, that he prouoke not the plague of vengeance.</p>
                     <p>Let vs therfore haue humilitie in our hartes: For as a wiſe man loketh well to his owne goinges, euen ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant are the wordes ſpoken in due ſeaſon, which moueth the woman in hir wrath vnto patience, whereof <hi>Salamon</hi>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:15694:41"/>ſayth: <hi>Faire wordes are an Hony Combe, a refreshinge of the minde, and a health of the bones.</hi> For it is ſeldome ſeene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any beaſt is found in the cruelſt rage, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Male doth euer hurte his Female: and how vnnatural a thing is it for a man to hurt his owne fleſh and body: Who will violently reuenge himſelfe (yea) on his foote if it chaunce to ſtumble? but wil not rather, if hee haue an yll bodye, cheriſh it to make it better.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The ſtrong</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Pawle</hi>) <hi>ought to beare the fraileneſſe of the weake, let one ſuffer with another: beare ye one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burden, and ſo shall ye fulfill the lawes of Chriſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thinge</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Peter:</hi>) <hi>Haue feruent loue amongſt you, for loue couereth the multitude of faultes.</hi> So that loue in all things and at all times ought to bee the whole doore and only inſtrument to worke and frame all things betwéene man and wife.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>VVhat the Husband ought to bee.</head>
                     <p>BY all this may yee geather and learne that the man is the head, gouernour, ruler, &amp; inſtructer (with gentil wordes and good example) the prouyder, defender, and whole comforte of the woman, and oweth vnto hyr moſt feruent loue and affection, all gentle behauiour, all fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and helpe, all comforte and kindeneſſe, as to him ſelfe, his owne fleſh and body: ſo that vnder God there is no loue, no affection, no fréendſhip, no nerenes of kin, to be compared vnto this, nor any one thing vnder the Sun that pleaſeth God more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man and wife that agrée well togeathers, which liue in the feare of God. And how can that bee more liuely expreſſed, then in that, that Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, and the holy chriſtian Church, and the holy body of them both, are ſet forth for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Mirror of the ſtate of Wedlocke, or coniugall loue, a more holy, a more godly and purer example could not be ſhewed. Vndoubtedly, this doth plainely ſhow, that loue Matrimoniall is moſt highly accepted afore God, and the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15694:42"/>contrary muſt néedes folow, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnquietnes, hatred, ſtrife, brawling, chiding, and frowardnes in Mariage, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diſpleaſe God, &amp; is clearely forbidden by <hi>Sainct Pawle,</hi> where hée ſayth: <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, fierceneſſe, and wrath, roaringe, and curſed ſpeaking be put away from you: be ye curteous and louinge one to another and merciful, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuing one another, euen as God for Chriſtes ſake forgaue you.</hi> Surely it is an highe and pure loue, perfecte and conſtant that God requireth to be betwéene maryed cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and therfore ought they by all wayes, meanes, and labour to get, maintaine, and increaſe this exceding loue, and to eſchue, forbeare, and cut of all things, that might occaſion any parte of the contrary.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>What maintaineth loue and quietneſſe in Mariage.</head>
                     <p>ANd vndoubtedly, there is nothing that longer main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth concorde and quietnes, nor more increaſeth perfecte loue in Maryage, then ſweet and faire wordes, gentle and fréendly déedes, and with a louing patience to take all things to the beſt. Fréely to breake their mindes togeathers, and al things to be kept ſecret, doth glad and willing to amend that is amiſſe, and aboue all thinge not once one to heare yl of another, for <hi>S. Pawle</hi> warneth you that ye giue no place to the backebiters, but take them as yll willers to you both, though that they be neuer ſo nere fréendes or kin. And God ſayth: <hi>A man shall forſake Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, and cleaue vnto his Wife, and they two shalbe one flesh, which in like caſe is mente to the Woman.</hi> Therfore ought no creature aliue, to be in ſuch eſtéema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, credit, fauour, and loue, as each of you with others. Alſo to bee of a ſober and temperate dyet, doth much far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a good agréement, and where the contrary is, there is much vnquietneſſe. For <hi>Salomon</hi> aſkinge where is woe? where is ſtrife? where is brawling? euen amongſt thoſe (ſaith hée) that bee euer at the Wine, therfore it is moſt cumly for chriſtians to be temperate in dyet, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15694:42"/>in wordes, temperate in déedes, and temperate in all things, ſo that at all times ye eſchue al exceſſe and furfet, rage and fury, which makes no difference betwixt man and beaſt, and all other things which may bréed any part of vnquietneſſe. For <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>Better is a dry mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with quietneſſe, then a full houſe, and many fat cattell with ſtrife.</hi> Therfore ought yee to exteeme and imbrace this concord and quietneſſe, as the maintainer and onely vpholder of the whole felicitie in Mariage, which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred of feruent loue, faithfulneſſe, and kindeneſſe, and maintained by the ſame, wherin ye ought continually to walke in all chaſtenes and purenes of liuing, which (aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly) ſhineth, as a moſt precious thinge in the ſight of God, and in the commendacion of the ſame ſayth:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The commendacion of Chaſtitie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SAlomon</hi> in the Booke of <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> O faire is a chaſt generacion with vertue, for it is with good men, where it is preſent men take example therat, and if it go away, yet they deſire it: it is alwayes crowned and holden in honour, and winneth the reward of the vndefiled Battel, but the multitude of vngodly Children are vnprofitable, and the things that are planted in whoredome ſhall take no déepe roote, nor lay any faſt foundacion, though they be gréene in the braunches for a time, yet ſhall they be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the winde, for they ſtand not faſt, and through the vehemency of the winde they ſhal bee rooted out, for the vnprofitable braunches ſhall bee broken, their fruite ſhalbe vnprofitable &amp; ſower to eate, yée meet for nothing, and why? all the children of the wicked muſt beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, of the wickedneſſe of their Fathers and Mothers, when they be aſked, but to the rightuous bee ouer taken with death, yet ſhall hée be in reſt.</p>
                     <p>Here may you ſée, how vile filthye and abhominable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Fornication, and Baſterdy is, and how high in eſtemacion a chaſte life is amongſt all good and godly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15694:43"/>folke, and eſpecially in the ſight of God, to whom no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creat ſinne is hid.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>That maryed folke ought to haue chaſte manners, and communication.</head>
                     <p>ANd as a chaſt louinge life in Mariage is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo ought ye to be of chaſt manners, to haue chaſt talke, and to eſchue all wanton faſhions, vnclenly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, filthy handling, and all vnſéemelyneſſe, and to be the ſpeakers and very doores of all vertue and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, for <hi>Sainct Pawle</hi> ſayth: <hi>Be ye folowers of God as deare Children, and walke in loue euen as Chriſt loued you, and gaue himſelfe for vs an offering and a ſacrifice of ſweete ſauour to God, ſo that fornication and all vncleaneneſſe or couetouſneſſe bee not once named amongeſt you, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Saincts neither filthy nor foolish talke, neither ieſting which are not cumly, but rather giuinge of thankes, for this ye know, that whoremongers, eyther vncleane perſons, or couetous perſons, which is the worshippers of Images shall haue any entrance in the kingdome of God and of Chriſte.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of temperance in Maryage.</head>
                     <p>ALſo there ought to be a temperance betweene man &amp; wife, for God hath ordained mariage for a remedy or medecine to aſſwage the heate of the burninge fleſh, and for procreation, and not beaſtly for to fulfill the whole luſtes of the diueliſh minde and wicked fleſh, for though ye haue a promiſe that the acte in mariage is no ſinne, if the man receaue his Wife as a guifte giuen to him of God, and the Wife her Huſbande in like caſe, as ye haue a promiſe that yee ſinne not when yee eate and drinke meaſurably with thankes giuinge, yet if yee take exceſſe or vſe it beaſtly, vilely, or inordinately, your miſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance make that yll which is good (beeinge rightly vſed and that which is cleane yee defile through your abuſinge
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15694:43"/>of it: <hi>God hath not called you to vncleaneneſſe, but vnto holyneſſe</hi> ſayth <hi>S. Pawle:</hi>) and farther (ſayth hée) <hi>It is the will of God euen that you should bee holye, and that euery one of you should know how to keepe his veſſell in holynes and honour, and not in the luſtes of concupiſcence as do the Heathen which know not God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo <hi>Sainct Pawle</hi> willeth you that yee withdraw not your ſelues nor departe not one from another, except it bee with the good conſente of bothe, for a time to faſte and to pray, which faſtinge and prayer, I would to God were more vſed then it is, not as Hipocrites were wont, but as Chriſtians ought, and are commaunded (almoſt) in euery parte of the Scriptures: for they that in eating and drinkinge fulfill the whole luſtes of the fleſhe, can not worke after the ſpirite: and as wée daylie and houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continually ſinne, ſo ought wee continually to praye and call for grace. And in all the whole Byble, you ſhal not finde a more godly example of maryage (which I would to God all maryed folkes would reade) then that of <hi>Tobiach</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Raguell,</hi> which were knit togeather in faſtinge and prayer, and oft vſed the ſame, lyuinge a godly, pure, and cleane lyfe: for the which, they obtayned the bleſſinge of God, and ſaw their Chiloerns Children to the fifte generacion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The commendacion of Children.</head>
                     <p>CHildren (vndoubtedly) is the higheſt guift, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt treaſure of this worlde, and maintenaunce of the ſame. For Children is the very ſure band and laſt knot of loue Matrimonial, by the which the parents can neuer be clearely ſeperated a ſunder: In aſmuch as that which is of them both cannot be deuided, ſeeing both haue parte in euery one. And children are their Parents chéefe ioy, comfort, and felicitie next vnto God, their ſtay and ſtaffe &amp; vphelders of their age: and in their children do the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents liue (in a manner) after their death. For they dye not all togethers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaue collops of their owne fleſh aliue
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15694:44"/>behinde them, and by their children (if they be vertuouſly and godly brought vp) then is God honoured, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth aduaunced, ſo that the parents and all men fare the better by them. Your children (moſt aſſuredly) is the very bleſſing of god, for the which ye ought to giue him moſt hartie thankes, and be contented, and with ſuch as hée doth ſende you, bee they many or few, Sonnes or Daughters. For if they be many, he wil prouide for them if they be faithful. If they be few, he may ſend you more, and giue you more ioy of one daughter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ten ſonnes: Therfore be content with his will, for hée doth all things for the beſt, and knoweth what is beſte for you, giue him moſt hartie thankes for ſuch as you haue, and be diligent to ſée them vertuouſly and godly brought vp, and in any caſe ſuffer them not to bee ydell.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How children ought to bee brought vp.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FOr they that wil not worke</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Pawle</hi>) <hi>let them not eate, therfore put them to learne ſome honeſt Science, or Crafte, wherunto of nature they be moſt apt. For in that shal they moſt profite, in the which they may get their owne ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, and ſerue the common wealth.</hi> And aboue al thing let them firſt learne to know God &amp; his moſt holy worde, which is the right pathe and highe way to all vertue and godlineſſe, the ſure Shielde and ſtronge Buckler to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende vs from the Diuell and all his cruell and craftie aſſaultes, giue them daily godly and louinge exhortaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuffer no vice to take roote in them, but rebuke them for their yll, and commend them in their well doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge.</p>
                     <p>Prouide honeſtly afore hand for all neceſſary thinges, both for them and all your houſehold. For ſaith <hi>S. Pawle to Timothie: If there bee any that prouideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his houſeholde, the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the fayth, and is worſe then an Infidell.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:15694:44"/>
                     <head>The order of your houſe.</head>
                     <p>OF the Sparrowes may yee learne the order of your houſehold, for as the Cocke flyeth too and fro, to bring all thinge to the neaſt, and as the dam kéepeth the neaſt, hatcheth and bringeth foorth hir yonge, ſo all prouiſion and whatſoeuer is to bee doone without the houſe, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the man, and the woman to take charge within, to ſée all things conueniently ſaued, or ſpent as it ought, to bring forth and nouriſh hir children, and to haue al the whole dooing of hir Daughters and women.</p>
                     <p>Alſo be louing vnto your children, and be not fierce nor cruell vnto them. For <hi>S. Pawle</hi> ſaith: <hi>Fathers rate not your children, leaſt they be of a deſperate minde, but with diſcrete admonitions, and with your pure and good example of liuinge (which is the cheefeſt perſwaſion) lead them to all vertue and godlyneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If all Parentes would vertuouſly bringe vp their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the knowledge and feare of God, in the practice &amp; exerciſe of ſome honeſt Science or Craft. Then ſhould we not ſée ſo many ydell as bee, ſo many Vacabondes, Théeues, and Murderers, ſo many vicious perſons of all degrées, nor ſuch vngodlynes raigne. But then ſhould wée ſée euery man honeſtly get his lyuing, preferring his Neighbours proffite as his owne, then ſhould wée ſée all men rightly do their duties, then ſhould loue and charity ſpring, and all godlyneſſe raigne, then ſhould the Lawes and Magiſtrates be willingly obeyed, the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth flouriſh, and God rightly honoured, for in this point only through the grace of God conſiſtes the amendment of all the whole worlde.</p>
                     <p>Therfore (my deare and welbeloued Chriſtians) ſéeing that in this bleſſed ſtate of Matrimony, and godly houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of huſband, wife, and children conſiſtes (next vnder God) the chéefeſt and higheſt felicitie of this worlde, and maintenance of the ſame, wherein the common wealth is wholly aduaunced, and God moſt highly honoured. I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15694:45"/>exhort you in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of the liuinge God, that you walke worthely therin, accordinge to the will of Chriſt, which you profeſſe without faining, and that you eſchue all woorkes and déedes of the fleſhe, which bee theſe, ſaith <hi>S. Pawle: Adultery, Fornication, vncleaneneſſe, wantonneſſe, Idolatry, Witchcrafte, hatred, varyance, wrath, ſtrife, ſedition, ſectes, enuyinge, murther, drunkenneſſe, gluttony, and ſuch like: of the which I tell you before, as I haue tolde you you in times paſt, that they which commit ſuch thinges shall not inherite the kingdome of God.</hi> Therfore follow yee the ſpirit and workes of the ſame, which hée (ſayth <hi>S. Pawle:</hi>) <hi>Loue, ioy, peace, longe ſuffering, gentilneſſe, goodneſſe, faithfulneſſe, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, temperance, and ſuch like.</hi> And yet once agayne, I exhort you with the exhortacion of <hi>S. Pawle. If there be amongſt you any conſolation in Chriſt, if there be any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable loue, if there be any felowship of the ſpirit, if there be any compasſion of mercy, fulfill you my ioy, that ye draw one way, hauing one loue, beeing of one accorde, and of one minde, that nothing bee done through ſtrife or vaine glory, but that in meekeneſſe of minde, euery one eſteeme other better then them ſelfe, and ſo shal you leade a ioyfull quiet, and godly life in this world, and after, through Ieſus Chriſt, come to the life euerlaſting, with God the Father, to whom bee all honour and glory. Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 10.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <q>If the roote bee whole, the braunches ſhall bee whole alſo.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15694:45"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
